<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A two-fold shaking of the earth: or, an exposition on Heb. 12.26, 27 Wherein is shewed, the first shaking of the earth, seems to be meant the putting down of the late King and bishops: the later shaking, a change of the present government. And reasons given for both. Also how, and in what manner this later earth-shaking may be according to scripture-prophesie: namely, by that earth-quake, Rev. 11.13 which is likewise opened. Lastly, here are many reasons given, why it may be hoped that this present parliament will prove to be that earth-quake (or at least begin the work) whereby the good old cause will be revived, the just rights of the people restored, and the nation setled upon a lasting and durable foundation of truth and righteousness. By John Canne.</title>
            <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C443AB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897180</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897180</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2473:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A two-fold shaking of the earth: or, an exposition on Heb. 12.26, 27 Wherein is shewed, the first shaking of the earth, seems to be meant the putting down of the late King and bishops: the later shaking, a change of the present government. And reasons given for both. Also how, and in what manner this later earth-shaking may be according to scripture-prophesie: namely, by that earth-quake, Rev. 11.13 which is likewise opened. Lastly, here are many reasons given, why it may be hoped that this present parliament will prove to be that earth-quake (or at least begin the work) whereby the good old cause will be revived, the just rights of the people restored, and the nation setled upon a lasting and durable foundation of truth and righteousness. By John Canne.</title>
                  <author>Canne, John, d. 1667?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for L. Chapman at the Crown in Popes-head Ally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ A⁴ B-H I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Earthquakes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry Drummond,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lbury Park. SURREY.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A two-fold Shaking</hi> Of the EARTH: OR, An Expoſition on <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26, 27.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed, The <hi>FIRST SHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KING OF THE EARTH,</hi> ſeems to be meant the putting down of the late <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops:</hi> the <hi>later Shaking,</hi> a change of the <hi>preſent Government.</hi> And <hi>Reaſons</hi> given for both.</p>
            <p>ALSO How, and in what manner this <hi>later Earth-Shaking</hi> may be according to SCRIPTURE-PROPHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIE: Namely, by that <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> Rev. 11.13 which is likewiſe opened.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Here are many Reaſons given, why it may be <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PED</hi> that this <hi>PRESENT PARLIAMENT</hi> will prove to be that EARTH-QUAKE (or at leaſt begin the work) whereby the GOOD OLD CAUSE will be revived, the juſt Rights of the People reſtored, and the Nation ſetled upon a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and durable <hi>Foundation</hi> of Truth and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOHN CANNE.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>L. Chapman</hi> at the Crown in Popes-head Ally. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135122:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou muſt be a ſtranger in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if thou haſt not heard of a people call'd <hi>Commonwealths-men</hi> and <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-men,</hi> and what <hi>grievous things</hi> are laid to their charge. Now I care not who thou art that ſhalt read this brief <hi>Apology</hi> for them, if thou be not like him, who ſaid, <hi>He would not be convinc'd, though he were convinced.</hi> The great accuſation raiſed up, and ſpread all the Nation over againſt theſe men, is, <hi>That they allow not Magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ates, neither would they have the people be un-under Laws and Government.</hi> I think I may confidently ſay, The Devil (who is the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lyars</hi>) never brought forth a greater untruth, nor had leſs whereby to palliate and hide his falſhood, then in this particular. For not only do theſe men approve of <hi>Laws,</hi> Magiſtrates, and <hi>Government,</hi> but there are none in the Nation, that do more deſire, pray for, and preſs after un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt <hi>Magiſtrates, good Laws,</hi> and <hi>a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Government,</hi> then they. But this is true (and the <hi>Court-party</hi> knows it) they are not for <hi>Tyrants,</hi> neither to have an <hi>Arbitrary power exerciſed over the lives, Liberties, and Conſciences of the people;</hi> but would
<pb facs="tcp:135122:5"/>have the undoubted Rights and Priviledges of the Nation ſetled upon a laſting and durable foundation of truth and righteouſneſs: they would have no violence or oppreſſion done to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, but all men, as men, enjoy their <hi>Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right;</hi> yea, and if it were poſſible, to deliver the <hi>whole Creation from that bondage and groaning under which it lies, into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the children of God,</hi> Rom. <hi>8.20, 21, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a man diſlike the ſtanding of weeds in a garden, doth it follow he is againſt the ſowing and planting it with herbs and flowers? <hi>Reader,</hi> open thine eyes, and <hi>look up like a man;</hi> here thou haſt the <hi>Caſe truly ſtated:</hi> theſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths-men</hi> and <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-men</hi> are not well pleaſed that the <hi>Engliſh Garden</hi> (or <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) ſhould be overſpread with the <hi>vines of Sodom,</hi> and the <hi>ſowr grapes of Gomorrha,</hi> Iſa. <hi>1.10.</hi> That <hi>perſons of corrupt intereſt ſhould impoſe (at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) heavy yokes upon the necks of the free-men of</hi> England. That <hi>the proud are called happy, and they that work wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are ſet up. That judgment is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way backward, and juſtice ſtands afar off: That truth is fallen in the ſtreets, and he that departeth from evil, maketh himſelf a prey.</hi> That ſuch weeds and traſh ſhould be in the GARDEN they do diſlike it, this is true: they both ſpeak againſt it, and mourn for it. But
<pb facs="tcp:135122:5"/>will any man of reaſon or ſenſe therfore conclude they are againſt all <hi>Magiſtracie</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but rather thus, <hi>they would have theſe hurtful weeds pluckt up by the roots, that righteous things might be planted in the room of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing that I ſhall ſpeak a little to, is to give the <hi>Reader</hi> ſome Reaſons of publiſhing this <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> After ſome ſeeking of God, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures; this I humbly conceive, that the Lord will begin to revive his <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> again by the <hi>Repreſentatives of the people.</hi> As he honoured and bleſt the <hi>long Parliament,</hi> with a good progreſs in the <hi>work of Reformation:</hi> ſo I think he will make yet further uſe of <hi>Parliaments</hi> for the publick good of the Nation. I ſhall not be abſolute what will be done at this time; but I have great hope ſomething will be done for the reſtoration of the Civil Liberties of the people. A wiſe General will hearken to the advice of a mean Souldier: <hi>I</hi> deſire no more but what is here ſet down for publick good may be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> It is a ſpecial work of Parliaments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the grievances of the people, and to be moſt ſevere (ſo Parliaments were wont to be) againſt ſuch men, who through the greatneſs of their power and place, take occaſion to oppreſs and wrong people the more. In this regard, I have thought it my duty, publickly to declare what
<pb facs="tcp:135122:6"/>injuſtice and hard meaſure we have had; as to be baniſhed, impriſoned, caſt out of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and livelihood; but never knew any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Cauſe why they dealt ſo cruelly with us. It is ſaid of <hi>Herod, And he ſent and behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded John in priſon,</hi> Mat. <hi>14.</hi> after ſuch a manner have our <hi>New maſters</hi> uſed us; ſent their Souldiers to our houſes, pluckt us out of doors, thrown us into priſon, but never told us for what, nor brought us to any Tryal. It is poſſible theſe things may meet with ſome Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament-men; if it do, I ſhall humbly propound this, <hi>Whether in point of Law and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thoſe publick oppreſſions whereof we complain, ſhould not be examined; and if found true, Whether ſuch men be fit to have the chief rule of the Nation any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> Major General <hi>Overtons Caſe</hi> will ſpeak loud enough to this <hi>Parliament,</hi> what New Maſters are lately ſtarted up.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Howſoever hitherto the ſons of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> have been too hard for us, and not only ſo, but of ſuch imperious and high ſpirits, as <hi>Pope-like,</hi> no man might ſay to them, <hi>Sir, Why do you ſo?</hi> There is ſome hope now (a poſſibility at leaſt) that a <hi>Parliament</hi> may give them a check: true it is, there hath not been for ſome <hi>late yeers</hi> a door open for the oppreſſed to bring in their complaints againſt ſuch perſons as did them the moſt wrong. So that the <hi>publick ſore</hi> hath run'd ſtill, becauſe there was not a
<pb facs="tcp:135122:6"/>coming upto the Cure. But it's hoped this will be a free <hi>Parliament,</hi> out of which <hi>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ributive Juſtice</hi> will flow, to the great refreſhing of the oppreſſed every where: it is to no purpoſe to cleanſe the pipes, and leave the fountain dirty; to ſweep down the cobwebs, and leave the ſpider to make more. Never had the <hi>long Parliament</hi> wrought that <hi>Reformation in England,</hi> and reſtored the Peoples Liberties in that meaſure they did, had they not fallen upon the <hi>SPRING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEAD,</hi> and caught the <hi>SPIDERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> To wipe off that common ſcandal which by <hi>Apoſtates</hi> is caſt upon us; <hi>i. e.</hi> that it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our frowardneſs and diſcontents that make us complain, otherwiſe we have nothing againſt them, nor any harm done us. <hi>Micah</hi> thought it a very ſtrange thing in the <hi>Danites,</hi> when they had taken from him his Prieſt and Idols, then to ask him, <hi>What he ail'd?</hi> We cannot take it little better then a ſcoff, when they r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b'd the people of their goods and freedom, and oppreſt them ſeveral ways by an <hi>Arbitrary power,</hi> then to twit them in the teeth with complaining. Juſt like a child, who having ſcratcht his mother, then cries, as if the wrong had been done to him. Thus having ſcratcht and torn the <hi>Mother Commonwealth;</hi> yea, upon the matter mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her, <hi>They cry out againſt the people, as being pettiſh and froward, know not what they would have,</hi> &amp;c. whereas it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves that have done the evil. But if
<pb facs="tcp:135122:7"/>this <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall ſit to judge between the <hi>Mother and the Child;</hi> we are ſure the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be quitted, and the Child ſhall have his due payment, not only for <hi>ſcratching,</hi> but for crying too.</p>
            <p>But <hi>5.</hi> And indeed this is a <hi>main Cauſe;</hi> that is, to ſhew, that in taking off <hi>heavy yokes,</hi> and executing juſtice upon oppreſſours, whereby righteouſneſs may be exalted in the Nation: here a <hi>Scripture-Propheſie will be fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not mentioned the <hi>Laws and Statutes of the Land,</hi> becauſe this by others is alreadie done. <hi>Mr. Pryn</hi> in a Book printed this <hi>yeer 1658.</hi> (and to which he ſets his name) affirms, (quoting many <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> for it) That <hi>the perſons now in power are theeves and robbers; yea, uſurpers, and have ſet up a new uſurped power, and have committed the higheſt Treaſon, and act againſt all Law both of God and the land.</hi> And for that Parliament, which, they ſay, <hi>gave them pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority:</hi> He ſaith, <hi>It was but a pretended Parliament, and a mock-Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and by the Acts of lawful Parliaments they were all Traytors.</hi> This is publick, and known to the Judges and Lawyers of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and what may we think, but by their ſilence they give conſent? <hi>See his Book Demophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, Appendix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now howſoever the <hi>Parliament</hi> having Law and equity on their ſide, have ground ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:135122:7"/>to be up and doing; yet it cannot be but ſome encouragement unto them likewiſe, if they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it is ſuch a work as the word of God in a ſpecial manner calls them to it. Doubtleſs it is an <hi>honour</hi> to be call'd unto ſuch a ſervice; but if it be done faithfully, not like <hi>Jehn</hi> for <hi>ſelf-ends;</hi> but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God, not only ſhall their memory be bleſt, but the Lord will remember them for good, and reward their work and labour of love.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay little more: <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> (ſaith Solomon) <hi>exalteth a Nation,</hi> Prov. <hi>14.34.</hi> Again, <hi>The Throne is eſtabliſhed by Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> Prov. <hi>16.12.</hi> Note, it is not <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophels counſel,</hi> nor <hi>Machiavels Head-piece</hi> will do it. I ſay further, It is not raiſing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and increaſing heavier burdens, or ſetling things this way or that way, will do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> Of a truth, <hi>God looks for righteouſneſs and judgment from us,</hi> Iſa. <hi>5.7. To do juſtice and judgment is more acceptable to the Lord then ſacrifice,</hi> Prov. <hi>21.3.</hi> This is better then faſting or praying; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>a morning Sermon at the Abby,</hi> or <hi>praying before the Houſe ſits.</hi> It is ſo good, that if <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>judgment</hi> be not ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cuted, the Lord abhors all ſacrifices, ſee <hi>Iſa. 1.15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the reſt of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knew who was the <hi>TROUBLER,</hi> had they only acknowledged that great wickedneſs, and mourned for it, and done no more, the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:135122:8"/>would have withdrawn himſelf ſtill from them, <hi>Joſh. 7.12.</hi> So when it was told <hi>David, The three years famine was for Saul and his bloody houſe, becauſe he ſlew the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, 2</hi> Sam. <hi>21.1, 2,</hi> &amp;c. Had there been no more then confeſſing the ſin, and asking par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the Lord would not have been entreated for the Land. So it may be ſaid of our preſent condition; ſhould there be a publick confeſſion made of our <hi>late Apoſtacie, Covenant brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, Treaſon, Oppreſſion.</hi> &amp;c. before God, Angels, and men, and ſolemn days appointed by the <hi>Parliament</hi> to mourn for it nevertheleſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>accurſed thing</hi> be deſtroyed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, it may be queſtioned, whether God will be with us any more. <hi>Faithful are the wounds of a friend: but the kiſſes of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy are deceitful,</hi> Prov. <hi>27.6.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135122:8"/>
            <head>A Two-fold Shaking OF THE EARTH: OR, An Expoſition on <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26, 27, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common received opinion, that <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in his <hi>Perſian</hi> Wars, by the light and information which he had from <hi>Jaddus,</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt of the Jews,</hi> who opened unto him the Viſion of the <hi>Ram</hi> and <hi>He-Goat,</hi> in which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> had foretold the overthrow of the <hi>Medes</hi> by the King of <hi>Grecia. Dan.</hi> 8. I know it comes many times to paſs, howſoever men in their actions fullfil the purpoſe and deſign of God, <hi>yet think not ſo,</hi> neither do it to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135122:9"/>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.7. Notwithſtanding the Lord (who is good to all) rewards them ſometimes largely for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake. And ſo much appears in the Prophet: <hi>Son of man, Nebuchad-rezzar King of Babylon cauſed his Army to ſerve a great ſervice againſt Tyrus; every head was made bald, and every ſhoulder was peeled: yet had he no wages, nor his Army for Tyrus, for the ſervice he had ſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I will give the land of Egypt unto Nebuchad-rezzar King of Babylon, &amp; he ſhall take her multitude, and take her ſpoyl, and take her prey, and it ſhall be the wages of his Army; I have given him the land of Egypt for his labour wherewith he ſerved against it, becauſe they wrought for me, ſaith the Lord God,</hi> Ezek. 29.18, 19, 20. Now had he and his Army done that ſervice conſcientiouſly, and in obedience unto Gods appointment, and therein ſingly have ſought the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and not their own profit and intereſt; would they not much more have pleaſed him, and done a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135122:9"/>more acceptable ſervice, and received a better and far greater reward?</p>
            <p>Hence this may be gathered: As there are great things to be done in the <hi>laſt days,</hi> by the <hi>Repreſentatives of the People,</hi> and by ſuch as ſhall have the Power of Nations in their hands (eſpecially, when it is <hi>to execute the vengeance of the Lord and the vengeance of his Temple</hi> upon any part of <hi>Babylon</hi>) that they have ſome underſtanding in the Propheſies of the <hi>laſt days,</hi> whereby they may know what their work is, and that they are call'd of God to it, and when and how to move in it. For ſo not only ſhall they be encouraged to take it in hand, but have aſſurance of good ſucceſs, and a full reward for their ſervice.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But we have not now men of Prophetical ſpirits, to open unto us the dark Propheſies of the Scriptures concerning the</hi> laſt Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Let this be granted, yet I humbly conceive, a man may take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and that very warrantably, to declare his opinion of the darkeſt and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135122:10"/>difficulteſt places of Scripture, in a ſober and modeſt way; and for this he hath <hi>a Cloud of witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, 2. It will be granted (I think) by all, when there is ſome part of a Propheſie already fulfilled, there is much light given to the knowledge of the reſt: I ſay, by that <hi>PART</hi> which is fulfilled, he that is wiſe, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the ways and works of God, may the better and eaſier underſtand what remains to be accompliſhed. Though <hi>a brutiſh man knoweth not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth a fool underſtand this,</hi> Pſal. 92.6. yet <hi>who is wiſe, and he ſhall underſtand theſe things; prudent, and he ſhall know them,</hi> Hoſ. 14.9. So then, this I would ſay, <hi>Though a man profeſs not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> nevertheleſs, <hi>from a due and ſerious obſervation of a Propheſie in part fulfilled; it is probable (being a perſon that fears God, and in dayly communion with him) what he apprehends by a diligent ſearch concerning the reſt, will prove to be a Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Do not <hi>Star-Gazers</hi> and <hi>Monthly Prognoſticators</hi> take large liberty at this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135122:10"/>time to publiſh to the world their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions concerning the <hi>alteration and change of States and Policies?</hi> as, what Kingdom and Commonwealth ſhall riſe or fall in ſuch a Yeer, or ſuch a Moneth; and what Deſolations there will be, by Peſtilence and Famine, by the ſword, and by fire and water; in ſuch Countreys, Towns and Cities: Notwithſtanding it is well known, (and confident I am it is a Truth) the firſt invention of <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is by many learned men attributed to the Devil. This is the judgment of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, lib. de habitu muliebri;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>de Idolatria:</hi> and of <hi>Origen, Hom.</hi> 13. in <hi>Num.</hi> and of <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus,</hi> in <hi>Eclog.</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi> writeth, as <hi>Coelius Rhodig.</hi> hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Aſtrologia, Auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Auguria, &amp; Oracula eſſe Daemono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inventum.</hi> And King <hi>James</hi> calls <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> the <hi>Devils School, Daemonol. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. I might add, how their profeſſion and practiſe hath been always condemned, for <hi>Impoſture, Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Superſtition,</hi> and <hi>Vanity,</hi> not onely
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135122:11"/>by the <hi>Fathers</hi> (as ſome call them) but by Councils, and divers learned later writers; yea, and more then all this, plainly forbidden in the word of God, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10, 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be ſo, that howſoever their profeſſion be condemned by God and men, yet there is freedom given them to publiſh their Aſtrological predictions, of <hi>the alteration and change of States and Policies:</hi> It will then be thought far more lawful, for any of the Lords ſervants to have the like freedom to declare his judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>the alteration and change of States and Policies,</hi> taking his light and ground from the word of God.</p>
            <p>For, 1. Howſoever there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing written upon the <hi>Stars</hi> or <hi>Planets</hi> of the riſe and fall of any Power or Government, Civil or Religious, yet in the holy Scripture it is. Here we have the <hi>Fourth-Monarchy, and the ten Kings, the little Horn, the Dragon, the Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Beast, and the two other Beasts; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer riſing up out of the Sea, the later com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135122:11"/>up out of the earth:</hi> not onely writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at length and fairly to be read, but the time exactly ſet down of their riſe, and how long they ſhall continue, and the period and end of them: <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. <hi>and</hi> 12.7, 11, 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2, 3, 9. <hi>and</hi> 12.6, 14. <hi>and</hi> 13.5. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though men are forbidden to ſearch the Planets, and the Eclipſes of the Sun and Moon for thoſe things, yet they are commanded and encouraged to ſearch the Holy Scriptures, even the Viſions and Propheſies which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the laſt days, whereby to know the <hi>Time of the End,</hi> Rev. 1.3. <hi>and</hi> 22.10. <hi>and</hi> 13.10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.9, 10. <hi>Surely the Lord God will do nothing, but he revealeth his ſecrets unto his ſervants the Prophets,</hi> Amos 3.7. Thus <hi>Noah</hi> knew the time when the Flood would come, before it came, though the ungodly knew it not. So <hi>Daniel</hi> knew the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of Gods people, a little before they were delivered, not by gazing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Stars,</hi> but by the light and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection which he had from the Word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135122:12"/>of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.1, 2. But this ſhall ſerve for the <hi>manuduction</hi> to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>The Scripture which I ſhall firſt mention, and ſpeak a little to it (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that meaſure of Grace which I have received) is <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26, 27. <hi>Whoſe voice then ſhook the earth, but now he hath promiſed, ſaying, Yet once more I ſhake not the Earth only, but alſo Heaven. And this word, Yet once more, ſignifieth the removing of thoſe things that are ſhaken, as of things that are made, that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken, may remain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I come to the opening and applying of this Scripture, I think it neceſſary to ſet down a few things, both to prevent objections, and for the Readers better underſtanding the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter treated of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be minded, that <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Propheſies</hi> have ſeveral accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments; that is, they are ſometimes fulfilled over and over, as to times, places, perſons: and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135122:12"/>be fairly concluded, Becauſe ſuch a Propheſie hath been once fulfill'd, therefore 'it cannot be fulfilled again. I could inſtance ſeveral Propheſies, which already have been fulfilled more then once, and yet are to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled again. To let paſs many others, when <hi>Moſes</hi> bleſſed the twelve Tribes, for <hi>Judah</hi> he prayed thus: <hi>Hear Lord the voice of Judah, and bring him unto his people; let his hands be ſufficient for him, and be thou an help to him from his enemies,</hi> Deut. 33.7.</p>
            <p>This Prophetical prayer of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſometimes in the whole, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in part, hath already at ſeveral times been fulfill'd, and yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie runs on for a further fulfilling. Read and compare theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 13.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>and</hi> 72.15. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.26, — 31. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.20, 21. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.35, 40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.15, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.4, 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 110.5, 6. So in that bleſſing which <hi>Jacob</hi> gave to the ſame <hi>Judah, Gen.</hi> 49.8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what he there by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135122:13"/>Spirit of God Propheſieth of, hath been fullfilled; and yet we are ſure there is much in the Propheſie to be fulfilled. For the Readers ſatisfaction, I have thought good to mention theſe places: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.41. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.32. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20, 21. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.12. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.14, 15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. <hi>and</hi> 14.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas ſome think in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Scripture-Propheſies</hi> to a particular State or Nation, this is too ſtraight, and miſſeth the mind of the Spirit; To this I anſwer: If in applying a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie to a particular Nation, it be there confin'd, then I grant there is a miſtake, if there be not a reſtriction in the Propheſie. But though the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie be general, and have a large extent, yet it is no ſtraitning of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, to ſay, that in reſpect of the riſe and beginning of it, it will not be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, but in ſuch a Nation at firſt.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135122:13"/>As light, though it ſpread it ſelf over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e face of the whole Earth, yet in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wning it breaks forth and appears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t in one place. The Lord ſaith, <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh,</hi> Joel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.28. Again, <hi>I will ſhake all Nations,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag. 2.7. Now I do not think that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſe things ſhall be done at one time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d all together; I mean, either of them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut gradually; that is, he will begin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mwhere firſt, and ſo proceed from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſh to fleſh,</hi> and from Nation to Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, till the whole be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But the greateſt difficultie is, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderſtand where the Lord will begin <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pour out his Spirit, and to ſhake all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions:</hi> For my part, I think, as the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tory of the old Teſtament reſpected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Jews, and we have little recorded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here of the affairs of the World, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Church and people of God were more or leſs concerned therein: for howſoever there were great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of things in the world (as we finde in humane Hiſtories) all the while the Kingdoms of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> ſtood; nevertheleſs, what reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135122:14"/>not the Church, the Holy-Gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> takes (as it were) no notice of. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Viſions and Propheſies of Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpecting the laſt days,</hi> do concern t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church and people of God; <hi>They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> written for their learning, Rom.</hi> 15.4. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore where the Churches a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there may we certainly expect the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pearance of them, eſpecially a begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And if this be ſo, I have the Reaſons to think, that the <hi>pouri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out of the Spirit, and the ſhaking of all N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> will begin here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Where the Lord draws o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the heart of his Children to ſeek h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> face for any particular bleſſing, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> uſually he grants it; <hi>Thou wilt prepar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their heart, thou wilt cauſe thine ear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hear,</hi> Pſal. 10.17. Now I think, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I may boldly ſay, Never were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearts of Saints in any age mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrongly carried forth by the Spirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God in prayer, then ſome have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe late yeers, for the particulars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Where may we expect th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work to riſe and be revived, but where
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135122:14"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was ſtopt, and had a Death (as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere) put upon it? What a <hi>Glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſe</hi> the Lord had in this Nation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow eminently he appeared with it, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well known: and alſo who they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, who through their hypocriſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Apoſtacie, moſt unworthily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayed it, and put an unbleſſed ſtop to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Scripture-Propheſies reſpecting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e laſt times,</hi> do moſt concern the Churches, and ſuch as make the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt profeſſion of Religion; ſurely then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Lord to begin the <hi>Earth-Quake</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, I ſay, <hi>Judgment at his houſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anctuary,</hi> it will make very much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he glory of his Wiſdom, Juſtice, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſs.</p>
            <p>For, 1. This I will ſay, and ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it againſt all gainſayers, That <hi>the Apoſtacy of Engliſh Profeſsors hath brought more diſhonour to God, and general ſcandal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Religion, then ever was done by any people profeſsing Godlineſs theſe thouſand yeers:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dd to this, How <hi>they glory in their ſhame, and declare their ſin as Sodom, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide it not,</hi> Iſa. 39.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135122:15"/> 2. They have brought (as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in them lies) all the Blood ſhed in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> three Nations, upon <hi>the good old Cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and ſeek to acquit the King and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Party, by building again the Tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Idolatry which was deſtroye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſuppreſſing with both hands, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which they pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The groſs hypocriſie of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors hath made more Atheiſts within theſe <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five yeers,</hi> then have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heard of in many ages before. Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I could name, who have confeſt, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obſerving the <hi>Horrible falſhood, treach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, lying, ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> &amp;c. among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors (eſpecially in the Officers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Army) are become ſtark Atheiſts for they thought it was not poſſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for men profeſſing ſo much Godlineſs and acting ſo much wickedneſs, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffered upon the face of the earth, <hi>I there were a God of Judgment,</hi> Mal. 2.17. Reader, wonder not at this, but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der there are not more Atheiſts, I had almoſt ſaid, <hi>all Atheiſts.</hi> For is there any thing that can occaſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135122:15"/>men ſooner and more effectually to turn Atheiſts, then to ſee great Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Religion; yea, Church Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Army Officers, even whilſt they are talking of Godlineſs, Juſtice, Honeſty, and whilſt they are faſting praying, and preaching, live in the practiſe of ſuch horrid ſins as heathens would abhor, and be aſhamed of? I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what a <hi>Turk</hi> ſpake to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of mine at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> when he had bid him leſs for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity then he asked: <hi>I am no Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> (quoth he) <hi>to ask otherwiſe then I mean to have.</hi> What would a <hi>Turk</hi> have ſaid, had he ſeen the actions of ſome Profeſſors of late yeers? <hi>I am no Chriſtian, to break all vows, oaths, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, engagements: I am no Christian, to cheat and cozen my Brethren, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of long prayer: I am no Chriſtian, whilſt I talk of Law and Justice, not to make conſcience of any thing: I am no Chriſtian, to preach against pride, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, ſelf-ſeeking; and in practiſe, no man more proud, more covetous, and more ſelf-ſeeking then my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:135122:16"/> 4. Howſoever the <hi>Good old Cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath met with great oppoſition; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> none have done that wrong and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to it, as <hi>Apoſtate Profeſſors:</hi> though the <hi>Scribes and Phariſes, with Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> crucified Jeſus Chriſt, yet it was <hi>Judas, one of the twelve</hi> that betrayed him, and delivered him up into their hands. It is true, Chriſt <hi>in his good old Cauſe</hi> hath been crucified by all ſorts of enemies; the old <hi>Malignants</hi> and <hi>Cavaleers</hi> trample it under foot, and laugh it to ſcorn, they ſhoot out the lip, and ſhake their heads at it: but who firſt betrayed it? who were they that delivered up the intereſt of Chriſt and his people into the hands of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men? <hi>It was not an enemy, then we could have born it;</hi> But they were Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and ſuch as we leaſt thought would have been ſo unfaithful unto God and their Countrey. <hi>Let death ſeiſe upon them, and let them go down quick into Hell: for wickedneſs is in their dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and among them,</hi> Pſal. 55.15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What will more ſilence them that are without, and awaken the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135122:16"/>Nations abroad, then to hear that <hi>judgment is begun at the houſe of God:</hi> ſurely if any thing will waken them, this will.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is to be heeded, though there are no people, Nation, or Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage under Heaven, but more or leſs are concerned in the <hi>Propheſies of the laſt times;</hi> yet every Propheſie is not to be carried to every Nation: neither do ſome Propheſies (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) belong at all unto ſome people. <hi>The five firſt vials</hi> (as I underſtand) will extend no farther then the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Beast;</hi> neither ſhall any part of the world be the <hi>ſubject of theſe vials,</hi> but the <hi>Antichriſtian State or Kingdom.</hi> Again, whereas Chriſt ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be Earth-quakes in divers places,</hi> Mat. 24. And certain it is, there is no Civil power, Government, or State upon Earth, but ſhall be broken to peeces, and utterly periſh; yet touching that <hi>Earth-quake</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. it will not be univerſal, but rather a <hi>State Earth-quake,</hi> in one Nation; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the effect of it will be wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135122:17"/>even to the ſhaking and overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the powers of this world.</p>
            <p>Moreover, as in Scripture we find many times <hi>part</hi> taken for the <hi>whole:</hi> ſo in Propheſies, as appears, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.16, 17. with <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though there be but a part of a Propheſie ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, yet <hi>Peter</hi> expreſſeth all. True it is, in all Propheſies, that which is done laſt, will be more full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then the former; yet ſo, as we muſt remember they have their morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or dawning, as their noon day. It is ſaid of the Angel, <hi>the Earth was light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his glory,</hi> Rev. 18.1. not at firſt, nor all at once, but by degrees: it will be ſo at laſt. It is ſaid, <hi>the ten Horns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Beaſt ſhall hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16. now this ſhall not be done by all of them; for ſome of theſe <hi>Horns</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake the whore, but ſhall go into perdition with her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.9, 10. <hi>and</hi> 19.18. To be ſhort, whoſoever would inform himſelf in the <hi>propheſies of the laſt times,</hi> let him obſerve theſe 5 things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135122:17"/> 1. The Lord will begin <hi>his work, his ſtrangework,</hi> amongſt that people where Religion is moſt eminently profeſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.18, 28. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though he <hi>ſhake Earth and Heaven</hi> together and at one time, yet the <hi>Earth</hi> firſt. As a man lays firſt the foundation, and afterward builds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; ſo the Lord will have righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and juſtice firſt eſtabliſhed in the Earth, and then <hi>men ſhall fear the Lord,</hi> (that is, worſhip him in ſpirit and truth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.13. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9.) <hi>as long as the Sun and Moon endure, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row all generations,</hi> Pſal. 72.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There muſt be a diligent and watchful eye to obſerve the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of <hi>Scripture-Propheſies;</hi> that is, how any <hi>Providential Diſpenſation</hi> gives forth the matter of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. For this is certain, if we ſee the Lord hath begun a work in order to the fulfilling of his Counſel and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, contained in any <hi>viſion</hi> or <hi>Propheſie,</hi> though there may ſeem to be ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, or a death upon it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135122:18"/>he will carry it on in ſpight of all oppoſition men and Devils: <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.1, 2, 20, 21. <hi>and</hi> 5.1. <hi>and</hi> 12.30, 31. <hi>When I begin, I will alſo make an end,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.12.</p>
            <p>And truly, I am of the opinion which the Army was of before their Apoſtacie, That <hi>the late King was one of the ten Horns,</hi> Rev. 17. And whereas he and his <hi>Monarchy</hi> were pluckt up by the root, and a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; here I take it, was a fulfilling of a <hi>Scripture-Propheſie,</hi> I mean a beginning of that <hi>good promiſe,</hi> Rev. 17.14. where it is ſaid, <hi>The Lamb ſhall overcome the ten Kings.</hi> And whereas there hath been a <hi>THING</hi> lately ſet up (I know not what to call it; for it is neither <hi>formally</hi> a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> nor a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> but <hi>tohu</hi> and <hi>bohu,</hi> without form and void:) To me it ſignifies no more then the <hi>houſe of the fooliſh builder, built upon the ſand;</hi> the wind and floods nigh at hand, will blow and beat upon it: and if ſo, it muſt fall, <hi>and great will be the fall of it.</hi> But the Lord (as I ſaid) will go forward to fulfil and perfect
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135122:18"/>the reſt of that Propheſie: ſo that it is neither the houſe of the <hi>Stewarts,</hi> nor the corrupt intereſt of any other man, that ſhall fruſtrate the Counſel of God concerning the Government of this Nation; but the good <hi>old Cauſe</hi> ſhall riſe again, and be more glorious then ever it was before.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Propheſies of the laſt times,</hi> as to their accompliſhment at firſt, they will be very dark and dubious. Truly, I think, without ſpecial enlightning by the Spirit, few of the Lords people will have a clear ſight and knowledge of what God doth, till a great deal be done.</p>
            <p>And one great Reaſon is, becauſe many think the <hi>ſlaying of the witneſſes, and their riſing, the Reign of the Little Horn, the laſt Apoſtacy and Earth-quake,</hi> will make ſuch a noiſe in the world, as the deafeſt and blindeſt amongſt the ſons of men will be able to hear and ſee ſuch things. But I cannot find in the word of God any footing for ſuch an opinion; but rather, that <hi>darkneſs ſhall cover the Earth, and groſs darkneſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135122:19"/>the people,</hi> even then, when <hi>Zions light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon her,</hi> Iſa. 60.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beware leſt thou ſtumble here with the multitude; that is, to think ſuch and ſuch Propheſies are not fulfilled, becauſe thou canſt not ſatisfie thy ſelf, when, where, and how they were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. That ſaying in the Prophet holds true here, <hi>Thy way is in the ſea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy footſteps are not known,</hi> Pſal. 77.19. A man that ſhall ſee the Sun at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, though he were aſleep when it roſe, will he conclude it is not the Sun, becauſe he ſaw it not at its riſing? <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou ſhalt ſee the <hi>Earthquake</hi> whereby the <hi>Power</hi> of this <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> is broken, the <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> on foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and righteouſneſs exalted in the Nation; ſuch as have baſely betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Rights and Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſervedly puniſhed, and ſo a way prepared for the 144000 to do the reſt of the Lords work, of higher and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concernment: I think thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt very well conclude, that the <hi>reign
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135122:19"/>of the bottomleſs Beaſt, the Little Horn, the ſlaying of the witneſſes and their riſing,</hi> all theſe things are paſt, though thou ſlepſt when they were doing. Now for the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Heaven,</hi> here, is meant <hi>States and Policies;</hi> the firſt, what is Civil and Temporal; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Eccleſiaſtical and Religious. By <hi>Shaking,</hi> is meant alteration and change; that is, removing and taking away all forms and kinds of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which now ſtand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.19. <hi>and</hi> 13.13. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.16. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. I know by others this is otherwiſe interpreted, <hi>i. e.</hi> a <hi>Shaking</hi> of the material Earth and Heavens, with all the Inhabitants thereof, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men. But under favour, there is nothing in the <hi>Prophet</hi> nor in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> that hath any reference to <hi>the judgment of the great day;</hi> and therefore this <hi>Shaking</hi> cannot be applied to that time, but muſt be before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>once more,</hi> I underſtand two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Government changed;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:135122:20"/>yet ſo, as there is ſomething afterward ſet up in the ſame Nation, ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto God, as <hi>THAT</hi> alſo ſhall be be deſtroyed, <hi>That thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken may remain.</hi> What the things are which ſhall remain after a twofold ſhaking, is ſhewed in <hi>Daniel: And in the days of theſe Kings ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom, which ſhall never be deſtroyed, &amp; the Kingdom ſhall not be left to other people, but it ſhall break in peeces and conſume all theſe Kingdoms, and it ſhall ſtand for ever,</hi> Chap. 2.44.</p>
            <p>By <hi>once more,</hi> is ſignified the great difference between the <hi>two-ſhakings:</hi> For howſoever the Lord doth both, and in the <hi>firſt ſhaking</hi> there was great expectation and hope of much good by it; yet through the hypocriſie and falſhood of ſome men, things proved altogether otherwiſe: <hi>He looked for judgment, but behold oppreſſion; for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but behold a cry,</hi> Iſa. 5.7.</p>
            <p>Now howſoever the Lord was pleaſed to ſuffer ſuch corrupt men to carry on their wicked deſign, and to ſet up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt his <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Zion,</hi> that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135122:20"/>the Scripture might be fulfilled; yet after the <hi>ſecond ſhaking,</hi> it ſhall not be ſo: but the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun) ſhall go forward and proſper; yea, and in ſpight of all Apoſtates and Hypocrites, under what profeſſion and form ſoever truth and righteouſneſs ſhall riſe and flouriſh for ever.</p>
            <p>Now indeed here lay the occaſion of a former miſtake generally among the Lords people: we thought when the <hi>King and Biſhops were taken away,</hi> and the form of Government changed from <hi>Monarchy</hi> to a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> that we ſhould preſently have ſeen good days, and that tyranny and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would have ceaſed; but we did not conſider the word here, YET ONCE MORE; <hi>i. e.</hi> there muſt be <hi>two ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</hi> So that the <hi>good days</hi> (or, <hi>the days of the Son of man</hi>) ſpoken of in Scripture, do not belong to the <hi>first ſhaking;</hi> neither may any that truly fear the Lord, and keep the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and have the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, expect any better time, till after the <hi>ſecond ſhaking:</hi> when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135122:21"/>this <hi>yet once more</hi> is over, then coms in the time, that <hi>the Lord will not be wroth with his people any more: violence ſhall be no more heard in the Land, nor destruction within thy borders. Thou ſhalt no more be termed forſaken, neither ſhall thy land any more be termed deſolate. He will break all bonds, and ſtrangers ſhall no more ſerve themſelves of thee. Then the houſe of Iſrael ſhall go no more aſtray, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be polluted any more with their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. The Lord will no more make his people a reproach among the Heathen, neither ſhall the wicked any more paſs over thee, but be utterly cut off,</hi> Iſa. 54.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62.4. Jer. 30.8. Ezek. 14.11. Joel 2.19. Nah. 1.15. precious Promiſes! Oh, how ſhould we deſire this ONCE MORE! <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By <hi>Voice,</hi> I underſtand the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments</hi> which the Lord hath raiſed up and brought together to <hi>ſhake the Earth,</hi> and his powerful preſence with them, enabling them effectually to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the good work he calls them to.</p>
            <p>Methinks there is ſomething here
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135122:21"/>(though it lie like gold cloſe in the Earth) very obſervable. There are <hi>two ſhakings,</hi> but the word VOICE is but once mentioned, and joyned with the <hi>first:</hi> the <hi>later</hi> brings a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with it.</hi> As if the Lord in this <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhaking</hi> would be more ingaged for the intereſt of Chriſt and his people then he was before. Though a man do ſomething freely and of his own accord, yet where he ſtands bound by promiſe, there he takes the more care to have the thing done. This may ſerve for our comfort and encouragement, the Lord will not fail us in this <hi>ſecond ſhaking.</hi> He ſeems to give us more then we had before; I ſay, more ground and reaſon to hope that this preſent Apoſtacie in Church and State ſhall be <hi>ſhaken,</hi> then we had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to beleeve the <hi>ſhaking</hi> of the King and Biſhops.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing our buſineſs at preſent, lies not ſo much in <hi>explanation,</hi> as <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> I ſhall therefore come now to ſet down what I humbly conceive, may be from the forenamed Scripture rightly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135122:22"/>gathered. Not reſtraining the Text to our preſent time, or only to that which is here aſſerted (for as I have ſaid, ſo I ſay again, both this Propheſie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be fulfilled over and over.) But that which I take the Holy Ghoſt hath ſome reſpect to in this Propheſie, &amp; foretels ſhould come to paſs, is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt ſhaking was, when the Long Parliament voted down Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and pluckt up Monarchy root and branch, and constituted a Commonwealth, and enacted, that the Supream Authority of the Nation ſhould be in a Parliament, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King and Houſe of Lords.</hi> Add to this (as proper to the ſame <hi>ſhaking) the extirpation of the Government of the Church by Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The ſhaking which is yet</hi> ONCE MORE, <hi>is the utter aboliſhing of that THING, which now ſtands.</hi> Reader, thou muſt bear with me: for truly I know not what to call it, except the LATE STATE-APOSTACIE: neither that <hi>THING,</hi> which is managed by the <hi>Tryers,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I ſhould ſay, it is one of the <hi>names of blaſphemy, which the great whore carries
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135122:22"/>upon her forehead,</hi> Rev. 17. (as I am perſwaded it is,) yet it hath no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name. But to proceed, <hi>theſe two things</hi> (call them what you will) <hi>being (as it were) the two preſent States and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies of the Nation; the one Civil, the other Religious, theſe both will the Lord ſhake; I ſay, Overturn, overturn, overturn.</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, let me requeſt this of thee, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear thy cenſure till thou haſt peruſed my Reaſons for what hath been aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I hope thou ſhalt ſee I am not like the Apoſtates of this age, to give rayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is without diſpute that among all Nations profeſſing Religion, there hath not been the liker <hi>State-ſhaking</hi> as was a while ſince in <hi>England.</hi> For not only was he (who was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by many LAWFUL PARLIAMENTS, the <hi>Supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate)</hi> brought as a <hi>Delinquent</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>High Court of Juſtice;</hi> but had ſentence of Death paſs'd upon him, the which was ſoon after put in execution; yea more, to the end that <hi>Monarchy</hi> might for ever ceaſe in the Nation,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135122:23"/>and the very name of it forgotten, there were <hi>four Acts of Parliament</hi> (all ſtanding yet in force, for ought I know) which make it <hi>high Treaſon,</hi> for any man to take upon him the name of a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Supream Magiſtrate,</hi> without conſent of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Act</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Be it ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and ordained, that whoſoever ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, publiſh, or any way promote any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be King or Chief Magiſtrate of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>or</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c. without conſent of Parliament, ſhall be judged and deemed a TRAYTOR to the Commonwealth, and ſhall ſuffer pains of Death, and ſuch other puniſhments as belong to the Crimes of high Treaſon.</hi> Act of Parl. <hi>January</hi> 30. 1648.</p>
            <p>The like <hi>Act</hi> was made <hi>March</hi> 17. 1648. and <hi>May</hi> 14. 1649.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>July</hi> 17. 1649. It was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>That if any perſon ſhall maliciouſly or adviſedly, publiſh by writing, printing, or open declaring,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the Commons in Parliament are not the Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Nation; or ſhall plot, contrive, or endeavor to ſtir up, or raiſe force,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135122:23"/>
               <hi>that every ſuch offence ſhall be taken, deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and adjudged by the Authority of this Parliament to be high Treaſon.</hi> But there is more yet; there was an <hi>Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which was drawn up and ſent out by the Parliament for all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſign, which went thus: <hi>I do hereby declare and promiſe to be true and faithful to the Commonwealth, as now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed without a King or Houſe of Lords.</hi> And this <hi>Ingagement</hi> was generally taken by ſuch as were then counted well-affected.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Though it cannot be denyed but this was a moſt eminent</hi> Shaking; <hi>yet how is it proved, that in the</hi> Change <hi>of the</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-Monarchy <hi>to a</hi> Commonwealth, <hi>a</hi> Scripture-Propheſie <hi>was fulfill'd, and particularly,</hi> Heb. 12.26, 27?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it be granted it was a <hi>SHAKING</hi> (and an eminent one too) it will eaſily be proved (being in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>) a <hi>Scripture-Propheſie</hi> was fulfill'd, and particularly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>For the Scripture-Propheſies <hi>of the laſt times,</hi> concern the Churches and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135122:24"/>people of God; and where theſe are, there may we expect will come to paſs what things are foretold in the word of God: there are many <hi>changes</hi> and <hi>alterations of States and Policies</hi> in the world at this time, of which nothing in Scripture is foretold: nevertheleſs where Gods people are, and Jeſus Chriſt is truly worſhipped, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any ſuch <hi>ſhaking</hi> (I ſpeak ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that light I have in the things of God) but in order to the fulfilling of ſome <hi>Propheſie. What thou ſeeſt, write in a Book, and ſend unto the ſeven Churches in Aſia,</hi> Rev. 1.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>England</hi> be one of the <hi>ten Kingdoms,</hi> in Dan. 7.7, <hi>and</hi> Rev. 17.12. as it is generally held; yea, the firſt that conſtituted it ſelf a free and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute State when the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> was broken to peeces; then I think it may certainly be concluded, that the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. hath reference to the <hi>ſhaking</hi> of which we ſpeak: my reaſon is this; <hi>What was revealed to</hi> Daniel, John, <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>was by one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and concerned one thing, as to the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135122:24"/>of the ten Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>firſt ſhaking</hi> was by a VOICE, I think there is very much in it (as I have hinted before,) Truly more VOICE then PROMISE; My meaning is, that many people in their riſing againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> were carried forth beyond their own principles: <hi>A VOICE</hi> there was; that is, God mightily appear'd in them and by them; but no Promiſe; that is, they had no <hi>Scripture-light</hi> for what they did, but only followed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, opportunity, victory, ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Reader, miſtake me not; I do not ſay there was not <hi>Scripture-ground</hi> for putting down <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> (I beleeve there was:) but this I ſay, many who had a great hand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, did it not upon that account; for there are many at this day (and ſome I know) who were as active and forward as any in the thing, and gave their <hi>Vote</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords;</hi> yet now, none more earneſt for a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> then they; yea, and for <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:135122:25"/>too, if it fall in with their Intereſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whereas it was <hi>Gods voice that ſhook the firſt Earth;</hi> I hope none will be offended (neither <hi>Independent, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> or <hi>Baptiz'd</hi>) if we ſay, ſuch as account themſelves the Lords <hi>Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, Angels of Churches, the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. are the perſons by whom the Lord chiefly ſpeaks; and his VOICE, as <hi>John</hi> was in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> This being ſo, by whoſe voice then was the <hi>Earth ſhaken?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer,</hi> By no <hi>voice</hi> ſo effectually as <hi>that voice which came out of the Temple.</hi> Oh! how did this <hi>VOICE</hi> ring tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Nation, calling upon the good people every where, in their <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> and <hi>Writings, to come forth and help the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi> never did this VOICE ceaſe, but was ſtill cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ears of the Parliament and <hi>Army,</hi> SHAKE, SHAKE, SHAKE, till they had <hi>ſhaken King and Biſhops out of the three Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very requiſite, as we have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the <hi>Voice from the Temple,</hi> ſo to give ſome inſtances how <hi>ſhaking</hi> it was,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135122:25"/>to have the late King cut off. I will begin with Mr. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> becauſe (I ſuppoſe) what he wrote, was the <hi>VOICE</hi> of all his <hi>Independent Brethren</hi> in that particular. Thus he tels us:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You muſt obſerve, That every one is ſubject to the Higher Powers: Mark, it is not to man firſt, but it is to the Power. Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Power, where-ever this Power lieth. It is not to the will of man, that hath Power, but it is to the Power of the man. Now the Power, the Authority, is that, THAT A MAN HATH IN A LEGAL WAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, in another place, <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no Authority we are ſubject to now, but according to the Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Country where we live. When things are brought into a Law, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Agreements and Covenants of the place and Country wherein we live,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then the power of God is in it. But we muſt enquire whether it be a Power.</hi> On Hoſ. Chap. 1. Lect. 6. p. 157. <hi>and</hi> Lect. 4. pag. 111. <hi>and</hi> Lect. 3. pag. 65.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bridge his Voice</hi> ſhall be next,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135122:26"/>in his anſwer to Doctor <hi>Fern,</hi> thus: <hi>Did not</hi> Athaliah <hi>remain as a conquereſs ſix yeers? and who knows not that ſhe was lawfully thruſt from the Throne again by a stronger hand then her own? Meer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest being nothing elſe but an unjuſt uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation. And if the Conquerer rule the whole Kingdom, &amp; keep them under by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt only,</hi> WHY MAY NOT THE SUBJECT RISE, AND TAKE UP ARMS TO DELIVER THEMSELVES FROM THAT SLAVERY? Mr. <hi>Bridge against Dr. Fern, Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 42.</p>
            <p>But one thing is remarkable, what ſearching Books there was, and citing the opinion of men. Truly, I think there was ſcarce a learned man (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Papiſt</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) if he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt Uſurpers, Tyrants viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Laws, Rights and Liberties of the People; but he was brought forth by thoſe who defended the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments cauſe againſt the King. To omit many, how often is <hi>Alstedius</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for ſaying, <hi>A Tyr ant without Title, who is an Invader, every private perſon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135122:26"/>may and ought to remove: for he is not a King, but a private man, who doth invade the Country as an Enemy.</hi> Alſted. Caſ. Con. cap. 16. Reg. 8. p. 341.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Chamier: All Citizens, or free Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, have a right or warrant to riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Tyrants, who by open force poſſeſs the Kingdom.</hi> Tom. 2. Lib. 15. cap. 12. Sect. 19. Again, Dr. <hi>Willet: Where the Kingdom is uſurped without any right, as by</hi> Athaliah; <hi>or where the land is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Invaders, as in the time of the</hi> Macchabees: <hi>in theſe Caſes there is leſs queſtion to be made of reſistance by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent of the States.</hi> On Rom. 13. pag. 592. Neither is King <hi>James</hi> left out: <hi>The publick Laws</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make it lawful and free, for any private perſon to enterpriſe againſt an uſurper of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Every man,</hi> ſaith Tertullian, <hi>is a Soldier enrolled to bear arms against all Traytors and publick Enemies.</hi> In his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtr. pag. 216.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not name any more cited by them. Touching this <hi>Temple-Voice,</hi> (wherein Mr. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> was louder then moſt of his fellows) there are 5
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135122:27"/>things to be ſeen in their writing, (when they ſtood with the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the King) as their <hi>State Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That an Uſurper hath no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is a meer private perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That no obedience is due to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled or illegal Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the ſword is peculiar to a Magiſtrate lawfully called, and not elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That to the being of a Magistrate, is required a lawful calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>To the making of a Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, is to go the Vote and conſent of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not mention this <hi>Voice</hi> to aſperſe it in the leaſt; neither do I think, they who ſtood with the <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the King had a bad Cauſe; nor do I condemn any man for the <hi>Publick Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> which he bore againſt the exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie and arbitrary actions of the late King: yet this I may ſay, and none will be offended at it but the guilty:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It cannot be juſtified in any man, to call that rayling, and <hi>ſpeaking evil of dignities</hi> in another, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135122:27"/>done by himſelf, was then accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture, Law and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Neither 2. can I judge it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then a fault, for any man to write againſt Tyranny, and preach it down in reference to the King, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in another allow and juſtifie the like <hi>Tyranny;</hi> yea, greater by many degrees.</p>
            <p>But 3. And this indeed I moſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſuch men, whoſe <hi>Voice</hi> never ceaſed againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> till their places were no more, ſhould be the forwardeſt to have that <hi>Tyranny</hi> up again, and exerciſed over the Bodies, goods, and Conſciences of the people, for which the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> were removed.</p>
            <p>Now for the next particular, <hi>i. e.</hi> our <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Reaſons</hi> why by <hi>yet once more,</hi> the <hi>ſecond ſhaking</hi> is meant; the <hi>ſhaking of this preſent State-Apostacie:</hi> I ſhall only touch one thing which lies in our way, and ſo haſten to it.</p>
            <p>As under the word <hi>Earth,</hi> in the <hi>firſt ſhaking,</hi> not only <hi>Kingly-Government</hi> is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135122:28"/>ſignified, but the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> alſo, called <hi>Earth;</hi> not only becauſe it was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with the other, but aſcended out of the <hi>EARTH;</hi> was meerly carnal and earthly, and had nothing of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> in it. So I take the matter here: Though this <hi>State-Apoſtacie</hi> have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it that pretends to Religion, as the <hi>buſineſs of the Tryers,</hi> yet this coms under the word <hi>Earth:</hi> ſo that <hi>Heaven</hi> afterward ſaid to be <hi>ſhaken,</hi> is another thing, in which the <hi>Tryers</hi> are not concerned.</p>
            <p>What was ſaid before concerning the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that their Government was earthly, carnal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is as true in the other; <hi>It is a plant not of Gods planting:</hi> yet in one thing the <hi>Prelates</hi> were to be commended, to the ſhame of theſe men; for that party would many times publickly undertake the juſtification of their calling, and would quote <hi>Fathers, Councils, Scripture,</hi> for what they did; but this <hi>later earth</hi> (as it ſeems by their ſilence) dares not put any thing forth for their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. They know they have no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135122:28"/>
               <hi>Fathers, Councils, Preſidents,</hi> or <hi>Scripture</hi> to warrant their unſanctified place and ſtanding. And in <hi>John</hi> there is a good Reaſon why theſe <hi>Tryers</hi> come not forth to the light: <hi>For every one that doth evil, hateth the light, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the light, lest his deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved or diſcovered,</hi> as hath the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>ſecond ſhaking of the Earth</hi> (for of <hi>Heaven</hi> I ſhall ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now) here I will follow the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer order: 1. Prove, that the preſent <hi>State-Apoſtacie</hi> ſhall be ſhaken. And 2. in this <hi>ſhaking,</hi> Scripture-Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſle fulfilled, and particularly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If the <hi>Rights, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges of the people</hi> ſhall again be reſtored, and the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> go forward to a good ſettlement of the Nation; then neceſſarily muſt this <hi>later Earth</hi> be ſhaken: for as darkneſs vaniſheth when light breaks forth; ſo all falſhood and treacherous deſigns of men muſt end and periſh, when <hi>truth and righteouſneſs</hi> take place: when the Lords time came that <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135122:29"/>be <hi>brought out of the Temple,</hi> and ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne, it could not be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but <hi>Athaliah</hi> and her confederates muſt <hi>ſuffer deeply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the reaſon why ſome endeavor what they can to uphold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs and all manner of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and cannot endure to hear of good Laws, and honeſt things, but hate ſuch perſons as would advance them. They tremble (like <hi>Felix</hi>) to think of righteouſneſs, and that there ſhould be ſuch a thing as men call a FREE-PARLIAMENT, <hi>and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the ſword.</hi> And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel: for being conſcious to what they have done, they cannot but expect to be rewarded according to their works. But let theſe know, notwithſtanding all their crafty counſel, and <hi>joyning hand in hand;</hi> the <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> which was in the Nation, ſhall riſe and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but they ſhall fall and periſh. <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate your ſelves, O ye people, and ye ſhall be broken in peeces: Take counſel toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it ſhall come to nought: Speak the word, and it ſhall not ſtand, for God is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135122:29"/>with us,</hi> Iſa. 8.9, 10.</p>
            <p>I was ſpeaking juſt now of <hi>Joaſh:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethinks in him we have ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at reſembles our <hi>good old Cauſe: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aliah</hi> doubtleſs thought ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>royed <hi>all the ſeed Royall of the houſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udah,</hi> and there was none left to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uniſhed her murder and Treaſon. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he was deceived, and found it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe. It is ſure enough, ſome thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey had utterly deſtroyed the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealth,</hi> when they made one man <hi>Chief Magiſtrate;</hi> but theſe workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uity will know ere long, it was a lie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd they wrought a deceitful work: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> (though an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant</hi>) was hid, as <hi>Joaſh,</hi> in the <hi>Temple:</hi> What if you ſay, By the <hi>Temple</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eant the hearts of all the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in the Nation? Again, though <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haliah</hi> cried, <hi>Treaſon, Treaſon,</hi> when <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oaſh</hi> was brought forth, yet it was no <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaſon</hi> in the people to ſet up their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awful King, and put her to death for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bloodie Traytor. So, <hi>if the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the people ſhall puniſh Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors, and Crown the Commonwealth with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135122:30"/>her juſt liberties and freedom, there will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no Treaſon in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> though hypocrites an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apoſtates, cry, Treaſon, Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>There is no queſtion, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Commonwealth <hi>be eſtabliſhed with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Rights and Liberties of the people <hi>but the Thing now up, muſt and will be</hi> ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. <hi>But how doth it appear, that</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good old Cauſe (<hi>like</hi> Joaſh) <hi>will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought forth, and</hi> crown'd with righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and truth? <hi>If you prove no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this, you ſay nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is very true, and I grant it therefore to prove it, theſe Argument and grounds I give.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Bitter root</hi> ſhall certainly be pluckt up, when thoſe things are done, for which the <hi>only wiſe God</hi> ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to riſe. And no doubt, among many other ends he had, it was,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To diſcover a multitude of <hi>rotte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hearts,</hi> whoſe hypocriſie before lay hid, either under a <hi>form of godlineſs,</hi> or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pretended zeal againſt the Tyranny and Idolatry of the <hi>King and Biſhops,</hi> and to have Church and State reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and having made their folly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135122:30"/>to all men, <hi>to lead them forth with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orkers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That a <hi>Scripture-Propheſie</hi> might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fulfilled; namely, the coming in of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>ſecond Apostacie,</hi> foretold in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the which <hi>Apostacie</hi> (to me) is as clear to be now in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Sun that ſhines at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. But of this more by and by.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To make proof of the faith, love, and obedience of his <hi>little flock;</hi> and in very deed, as the <hi>Tryals</hi> and <hi>Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns of the Lords witneſſes,</hi> have been theſe <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five yeers,</hi> many ways very great; So they have ſhewed much faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Lord, and to his <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Zion,</hi> that they have choſen bonds, baniſhments, cloſe impriſonment, and loſs of trade and livelihood, rather then with <hi>baſe time-ſervers, and merce-mary flatters,</hi> to betray the Liberties, Laws, and Rights of the Nation, for filthy lucre ſake. If a maid, that ſhe might be ſuch a mans wife, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a great eſtate, and live very poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him, would not this argue ſhe married him for LOVE and nothing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135122:31"/>elſe? How many are there to my know ledge, would they have broken the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Vows, Oaths, and Ingagements, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> joyned with others, to build agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what before they had deſtroyed, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might have had what honour, prefe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or place they would? But the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would rather be impriſoned and ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and ſuffer with joy the ſpoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their goods, then turn <hi>Judaſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for a few pence. But what love an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affection have theſe perſons in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhewed to the <hi>good old Cauſe,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> juſt Rights of their Country!</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Hypocrites having gotte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the preſent Apoſtacie <hi>fat paſture</hi> might the ſooner fill up the meaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their wickedneſs, and ſo be <hi>prepare for the day of ſlaughter.</hi> As the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will have the <hi>harveſt</hi> and <hi>vintage rip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> before he cuts them down: ſo there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing will ſooner <hi>ripen</hi> corrupt me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then greatneſs, honour, riches, <hi>&amp;c. Swi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not fatten faſter by acorns, then will a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hypocrite by Court-preferment.</hi> Now Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, conſider, as the Lord had theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and other ſuch ends for which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135122:31"/>this root of bitterneſs to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; ſo having had his END, what is now to be expected but a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den plucking of it up?</p>
            <p>Then 2. What is it that hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned prophane perſons <hi>to blaſpheme the holy name of God,</hi> more then the late deſtroying of that <hi>good work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> begun in the Nation? What ſaith the Scoffer at it! <hi>This man began to build, but was not able to finiſh it,</hi> Luk. 14.30. It is not man now, but God, the living God, that is derided and laugh'd at: <hi>he began to build,</hi> &amp;c. he made a fair beginning (ſaith the MOCKING-APOSTATE) to have had a <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> he ſeem'd as if he would have made a <hi>righteous Nation.</hi> and the people no more under the luſt and will of men. But ſome were too hard for him, and out-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, and undid all that he had done before, with the infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Blood and Treaſure. But know (thou Atheiſt) <hi>Jehovah</hi> is more jealous of his glory and great Name, then to give it to another. Though <hi>he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135122:32"/>have kept ſilence, and thou thoughteſt that he was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf;</hi> yet know, he will ariſe for his Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake. For ſo is his promiſe, <hi>I will ſanctifie my great Name, which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned among the Gentiles, which ye have prophaned in the midſt of them,</hi> Ezek. 36.23. But never will the name of God be recovered in this Nation, to the ſtopping of the mouths of Apoſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſphemers, until that bleſſed work of <hi>breaking Tyranny and Idolatry (begun in the Long Parliament) be on foot again.</hi> I ſay once more (as a truth which I hope the Lord will enable me if call'd to it, to ſeal with my blood) <hi>That the precious Name of God prophaned in this Nation by</hi> Apoſtate Profeſſors, <hi>will not be ſanctified, till the</hi> good old Cauſe <hi>be revived, the Freedom and juſt Liberties of the people reſtored, a Commonwealth ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon right principles of truth and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and thoſe who have been the cauſe of the late horrible revolt brought forth to Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Such are the wounds in the Body of this Nation, and the grievances and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135122:32"/>Breaches ſo many and great, as I am perſwaded, all the <hi>State-Phyſitians</hi> (I ſpeak not of <hi>Mountebanks</hi> and <hi>Quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvers</hi>) will perceive (when they ſhall come to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Cure</hi>) there is no healing of the whole, without cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a part off; and what that <hi>part</hi> is, they will ſoon ſee. The Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> ſpeaking of the falſe Prophets of his time, ſaith, <hi>One built up a wall, and lo, others daubed it with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> Ezek. 13.10. He alludes unto a <hi>fooliſh builder,</hi> who coming to a wall with his tools, ſees it is ſo rent and torn, as it cannot ſtand, but muſt be all pluckt down, and a new wall rais'din the place of it; nevertheleſs, he only plaiſters it over, and ſo ſeeks to cover the fault, but not to mend it. Who ſhould be <hi>builders,</hi> if not the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the people?</hi> And therefore if the <hi>wall before them</hi> (which others built) be ſo weak, ſandy, and totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that it muſt be <hi>ſhaken;</hi> ought they not to beware <hi>of dawbing it with untempered mortar?</hi> and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord wants not <hi>labourers,</hi> but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135122:33"/>if <hi>one company</hi> of men prove unfaithful; that is, <hi>will be dawbing a rotten wall,</hi> when they ſhould caſt it down, he will <hi>DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOLVE THEM</hi> with more ſhame and diſhonour, then any <hi>Protector</hi> could put upon them; and call ſuch to the <hi>State-work</hi> as ſhall be more faithful, and well rewarded for it. <hi>Say unto them which dawb with untempered mortar, that it ſhall fall, there ſhall be an overflowing ſhowr, and ye, O great hail-stones, ſhall fall, and a ſtormy wind ſhall renit. Lo, when the wall is fallen, ſhall it not be ſaid unto you, Where is the dawbing wherewith ye have dawbed it? Thus will I accompliſh my wrath upon the wall, and upon them that have dawbed it with untempered mortar, and will ſay unto you, The wall is no more, neither they that dawbed it,</hi> Ezek. 13.11, 12, 15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It may rationally ſatisfie all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byaſſed perſons, that <hi>Gods actings</hi> and <hi>appearances</hi> were formerly ſuch for the <hi>intereſt of Christ and his people,</hi> as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be, that he ſhould leave it afterward. What! was the <hi>King</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off? his Poſterity laid aſide? the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135122:33"/>
               <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Government</hi> put down, for this end, that there ſhould riſe up in their places, <hi>a Generation of men</hi> more corrupt then they were? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we will give credit to the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſpeeches publiſhed to the world by <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> it ſhould be ſo; that is, all the victories and deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the Lord gave unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the time of the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> was for them; that is, for their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt. They bluſh not to tell us in print (as may be gathered from their words plain enough) that Gods helping us in our ſeveral ſtreights, was to keep up the <hi>Lawyers in their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Prieſts in their oppreſſion; the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in perſecution; the Tryers in their beastly invention;</hi> and <hi>the old Malignant</hi> to take his revenge on honeſt men, for their former good ſervice to God and their Country. But I ſhall leave theſe <hi>mockers</hi> to him that <hi>will not be mockt by them,</hi> but one day ſtop their mouth with a witneſs.</p>
            <p>For concluſion, <hi>If the Lord were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to kill us, he would not have ſhewed us
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135122:34"/>all theſe things,</hi> Judg. 13.23. We may be confident, never would he have drawn out ſo many <hi>heart-groans</hi> from his people, much leſs ſo much bloud from them, even <hi>heart-blood</hi> (willingly ſacrificed in <hi>the high places of the field</hi>) for the <hi>good old Cauſe,</hi> had he not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to crown it with glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the end.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And here is a fit place to remind the <hi>Reader;</hi> as the Lord eminently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared with us in the time of the <hi>long Parliament:</hi> ſo on the contrary, ſince this OTHER THING came up, how viſibly and ſenſibly hath he ſhewed his <hi>ſignal diſpleaſure</hi> againſt us, for our baſe <hi>backſliding;</hi> laying a <hi>curſe</hi> (as it were) upon all publick affairs almoſt, (as he did on the <hi>fig-tree</hi>) that nothing ſhould proſper which they took in hand? I ſhall not ſpeak of that <hi>Golgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> the field of <hi>Engliſh skulls and blood;</hi> nor the many <hi>millions of Treaſure,</hi> waſted meerly to ſatisfie the luſts and will of ſome men; nor what ſhame and diſhonour the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lies under, being ſome yeers paſt a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135122:34"/>terrour to all Enemies about us. Let us come to conſider the preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nation: Ask the Souldiers what their Arrears are? Then enquire among the Seamen, how many months pay is due to them? and while you are there, caſt an eye upon the <hi>Navy,</hi> and ſee in what a <hi>pickle</hi> that is, and whether there be any proviſion to ſet out a Fleet either offenſive or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five. Add unto all this, the extream poverty of the people, as having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trade nor mony.</p>
            <p>It is probable, there will be in the next <hi>ſitting,</hi> ſome that were Members of the <hi>Long Parliament;</hi> theſe men do know in what a riſing and flouriſhing condition the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was, when they were diſſolv'd. But how are they like to find it now? as a poor ſheep full of worms; the worms are fat and luſty, but the ſheep lean, languiſhing and ready to periſh. So they ſhall ſee now (and not a few) perſons that are grown <hi>fat</hi> and <hi>full, by devouring the fleſh of the Commonwealth;</hi> I mean her Laws, Liberties, Rights, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135122:35"/>but for the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> ſo maugre and lean, as it cannot be long liv'd, if the Lord raiſe not up ſome good ſhepherds, to look after it.</p>
            <p>A man that hath ſpent much time and labour, and been at great coſt in a work, and no ſooner hath done it to his liking, but ſhould ſee it preſently broken before his eyes, would not this extreamly grieve him? ſuch as ſate in the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> and ſtood faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the <hi>good Cauſe,</hi> do well know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Monarchy was ſhaken, and a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth eſtabliſhed,</hi> they had hard work, and it coſt the Nation not a little blood and treaſure: for ſuch men therefore to ſee all that they did broken to peeces before their eyes, methinks it ſhould much affect them. What elſe they ſhould do, I leave it to themſelves, or rather to divine Providence: For <hi>God ſtandeth in the congregation of the mighty, he judgeth among the Gods,</hi> Pſa. 82.1. <hi>Saul</hi> a little before his end fell into ſuch ſtreights, as he knew not what to do. I know who have formerly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>neceſſity,</hi> when there was none:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135122:35"/>but now its fallen upon them to the full; for had it not been <hi>NECESSITY,</hi> this <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had never been call'd: what the iſſue will be, a little time will ſhew. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>The wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hand,</hi> Pſal. 9.16.</p>
            <p>It is very obſervable, that the Lord meets with oppreſſours and deceitful men, <hi>one of theſe two ways;</hi> that is, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall take the <hi>better</hi> way for his people, or the <hi>worſe</hi> way for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: When <hi>Herod</hi> charged the <hi>Wiſe men to bring him word where the yong child was,</hi> Mat. 2. here he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not a <hi>ſubtle ſerpent,</hi> not <hi>wiſe in his generation:</hi> for to have had his bloody deſign done indeed, he ſhould have gone himſelf, or ſent ſome of his guard to have done it. But in this <hi>way</hi> God blinded him, and kept it from him, that he might take a <hi>better way</hi> for Chriſt's preſervation. So <hi>Jezebel,</hi> had ſhe ſent ſome of her <hi>Prieſts</hi> with Souldiers to <hi>Elias</hi> (when ſhe ſent only a <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to tell him what ſhe would do by to morrow) that had been a ſure way to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135122:36"/>have diſpatched him preſently: but God would not ſuffer her to take <hi>that way;</hi> ſhe muſt chuſe another way, and a better way for the Prophets life.</p>
            <p>Again, Tyrants many times <hi>chuſe the worſe way for themſelves;</hi> thus it was with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> at the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> he had <hi>two ways</hi> to chuſe, either to return the way he came (which indeed was the better way) or to go forward and follow <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> into the great waters; <hi>but he will into the Sea:</hi> now in this he appeared more blind and hardned then before; for he might well think, the Lord had not made a way thorow the Sea for him, but rather had laid a ſnare for him and his Hoſt. I am now wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee what will be the carriage of ſuch men, who have <hi>betrayed their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:</hi> they have methinks (like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) <hi>two ways;</hi> the one is to RETURN, <hi>or</hi> PUBLICK REPENTANCE, that is, make a free and ingenuous confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their former treaſon, oppreſſion, Covenant-breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to give up all their pretended Authority and Power into the hands of the Peoples
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135122:36"/>
               <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> Doubtleſs of the <hi>two ways, this is the better:</hi> the other is <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh</hi>-like to go forward, though they cannot but think that this Great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly (like the <hi>Red-Sea</hi>) will ſave the Rights, Liberties, and good Laws of the Nation, and drown <hi>Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> oppreſſion, treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Power and Majeſty of <hi>Engliſh Parliaments</hi> (which have been) be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly heeded; it would not ſeem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together improper to liken them (at leaſt ſome which have been the beſt and moſt glorious) to the <hi>Red-Sea.</hi> For many proud <hi>Pharaohs</hi> with their Hoſts have been ſwallowed up in <hi>Englands Parliaments!</hi> Had not I ſeen ſo many unworthy <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> I ſhould not have thought there had been ſo much <hi>baſe Engliſh blood</hi> in the Nation, men of ſuch mercenary, low, ſervile, and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Spirits; ſo far from following the ſteps of their Anceſtours, in ſtanding up for the Freedom and juſt Liberties of their Country, as they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to maintain a private intereſt againſt the power of the people and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135122:37"/>Priviledges of Parliament. But it is well that there is a <hi>Publick Atteſtation</hi> againſt them, of many thouſands Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and well diſpoſed people, who ſay, <hi>We teſtifie and declare againſt the late flattering Addreſſes, which have been contrived and carried on by intereſted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as tending to the preventing the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of a Parliament; as alſo antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating (if not concluding) their ſence and judgment when aſſembled. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them a tendencie to the dividing of the people, and conſequently rayſing a new war, if God do not wonderfully prevent.</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtat. Novemb. 20. 1658.</p>
            <p>Before I end, there is one thing I deſirouſly deſire the Reader to obſerve (eſpecially if he be a Member of this <hi>Parliament:</hi>) in all their late <hi>Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> we do not find, that a <hi>Parliament</hi> is ſo much as nam'd, or once deſired: Hence it may appear, who were the <hi>contrivers</hi> and <hi>promoters</hi> of them, and for what end they came forth; not to have any oppreſſion or heavy burdens taken off; not that the Peoples Rights and Liberties might be reſtored, the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135122:37"/>ſeveral grievances in the Nation might be look'd into and remedied; not that corrupt men lately crept into places might be removed, and better choſen: No ſuch things were aymed at; for had they not intended to keep up the grievous corruptions in the Nation, they would not have diſcovered (as they did by their ſilence) ſuch a ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſregarding of <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having given many <hi>Reaſons</hi> that this <hi>Earth-Power</hi> will be <hi>ſhaken;</hi> The next thing is, to ſhew how in this <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> a <hi>Scripture-Propheſie</hi> is fulfill'd, and particularly <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27.</p>
            <p>Here I muſt re-mind the <hi>Reader</hi> of what was ſaid before, <hi>That Scripture-Propheſies do eſpecially concern the Church and people of God:</hi> and it is for them to heed and obſerve, how the Lord in his <hi>Providential Diſpenſations</hi> brings them to paſs, whether it be in beginning, proceeding, or ending.</p>
            <p>Our firſt Argument is thus: <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Earth-ſhaking coms not within the verge of the Text,</hi> Heb. 12. <hi>yet that Earth-government doth; namely, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135122:38"/>ſhall not only be first ſhaken, but alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a way is made and prepared for the Lord to proceed to the ſhaking of Earth-Powers in other Nations: But ſuch is this Earth-power or preſent Government,</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only endeavor to prove that part of the Argument which is queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable; that is, how this <hi>ſhaking</hi> aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted will be the firſt, and make way for the reſt, foretold <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the Lord begin a work, and ſomething <hi>stop</hi> it, his manner is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move that <hi>stop,</hi> and there to take up the work again and proceed: thus it was in the building of the <hi>ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> after there was ſome good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs made in the work, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 3. by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes</hi> command <hi>the people ceaſed,</hi> Ez. 4.23, 24. But the Lord (whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſhall ſtand) took off (by <hi>Darius</hi>) that <hi>ſtop,</hi> and ſo they went forward with the building, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 6. I have ſhewed before, that <hi>Gods work</hi> began, concerning the <hi>overcoming of the ten Kings,</hi> and preparing the way for the glorious and viſible Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, when the <hi>Old Parliament</hi> ras'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135122:38"/>down <hi>Kingly-Government,</hi> and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted a <hi>Commonwealth:</hi> that there was a ſtop made, it is true, and we know who were the occaſion of it.</p>
            <p>Truly, ſo wonderfully did <hi>the Lord of Hoſts</hi> go forth then with our <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> as among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then they began to ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for them,</hi> Pſa. 126.2. Not only were the Nations awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about us, and began to conſider, whether <hi>the day of the Lamb and his great power were not come:</hi> but likewiſe the Enemies amongſt us, began to <hi>give Glory to God,</hi> and would often confeſs, that God was with us and againſt them. What ſhall I ſay (ah! theſe things cannot be remembred without <hi>great thoughts of heart</hi> by all that are truly godly!) <hi>That bleſſed cauſe of truth and righteouſneſs</hi> did ſo proſper both at home and abroad, that had there not been an <hi>unhappy ſtop</hi> put to it (through the hypocriſie and falſhood of ſome men) it would have been ere this time in other Nations, <hi>conquering and to conquer;</hi> yea, probably before now, more
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135122:39"/>of the <hi>ten Horns</hi> had been cut off. For we were as a <hi>Beacon</hi> upon a hill, all people looking on, to ſee what would be the event of <hi>this Act, this strange Act in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This puts me in mind of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims,</hi> when they were ſmitten with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merods,</hi> they take counſel, to know, whether the <hi>God of Iſrael</hi> had done it or no: having therefore put the <hi>Ark of the Lord</hi> upon <hi>a new cart,</hi> and ſent it away, thus they ſpeak one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>If it go up by the way of his own coaſt to Bethſhemeſh, then he hath done us that great evil. But if not, then we ſhall know it was not his hand that ſmote us, it was a thing that happened to us,</hi> 1 Sam. 6.9. Whilſt the nations abroad, and the Enemies at home were muſing about the <hi>great cauſe</hi> we had in hand, what it ſhould mean; If it had gone directly forward, as the <hi>kine took the ſtrait way to the way of Bethſhemeſh, and turned not aſide to the right hand or to the left,</hi> v. 12. in all likelihood there would have remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this time no more doubtings concerning the work; but they would
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135122:39"/>have been fully ſatisfied (as the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stims</hi> were) that it was <hi>the Lords doing;</hi> but when they ſaw the <hi>work</hi> went not the <hi>ſtrait way,</hi> but there was a grievous turning aſide, no leſs then building a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the things which were deſtroyed, and deſtroying what was built; this took them quite off, and ſo blinded them, as now they can ſee nothing of God in the thing, but cry out, <hi>It was a Chance,</hi> neither was the Lord more with the Parliament then with the King: but all is now, <hi>It was the Fortune of War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have the Apoſtates by caſting the Lords work behind their back, and ſetting up their own intereſt, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many thouſands (far and neer) not only to ſpeak evil of the Good Cauſe it ſelf, but to deprive the Lord of his due Glory and praiſe; for that honour vvhich men vvould have given to the Lord (and it was even upon their hearts and in their mouths to do it) is now by this turning aſide, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him, and given to <hi>Idol-Fortune.</hi> Beſides, vvhat dread and fear vvas
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135122:40"/>there ſomwhile ſince upon the hearts of <hi>Cavaleers;</hi> no other then a kind of convincement, that to vote or fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>good Cauſe,</hi> vvas to vote and fight againſt God: but ſince this late Revolt brake forth, that fear (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) is over. So that now, if there be a door open for them in Parliament or Army, they will as readily vote and fight againſt the intereſt of Chriſt and his people, as ever they did before. <hi>O wretched Apoſtacy!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord vvill begin to <hi>ſhake the Earth the ſecond time,</hi> vvhere he ſees it is firſt ripe. As a husbandman that hath much corn to reap, cuts it not down all at once; but vvhere the ripeſt is, there he begins. Now among the Regions of the Earth, that <hi>Field</hi> is neereſt the <hi>ſickle,</hi> vvhere Religion, Conſcience, and the vvorſhip of God are made cloaks for fin and wickedneſs: SIN may be confidered as <hi>ſingle</hi> or <hi>double:</hi> if it have <hi>Religious hypocriſie</hi> mixt with it, it is <hi>a double ſin,</hi> and ſo ripens the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and haſtens his judgment the ſooner.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:135122:40"/>
            <p> Had the <hi>Scribes and Phariſees which devoured widows houſes under a ſhew of long prayer,</hi> Luk. 20.47. pickt theſe poor womens pockets, or cut their purſes, their ſin and condemnation had not been ſo great, as to cheat them in the vvay they did. It is ſaid of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, He ſent and Beheaded John in priſon,</hi> Mat. 14.10. though this were a moſt cruel act in the Tyrant, yet (I think) it vvas not half ſo bad, as that in <hi>Jezebel,</hi> vvho took away <hi>Naboths</hi> life and goods under pretence of Law, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Religion: It vvas no marvel, that Gods revenging hand vvas pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon her for it; for ſuch a ſin as that vvas, made her ſoon ripe for <hi>cutting down.</hi> Among other Reaſons perſwading me to think ſome terrible <hi>Earth-ſhaking</hi> is upon us, truly this is one; namely, that never ſo much <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional wickedneſs</hi> vvas in any age, as hath been of late committed in <hi>theſe three Nations</hi> under Religious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>viz.</hi> faſting, prayer, vveeping, talking high of God, and his <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Zion;</hi> juſt as did the <hi>Phariſees:</hi> all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135122:41"/>of late times (not of houſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but) of the lives and liberties of the people, is <hi>ex parte altiſſimi,</hi> for the moſt high God. As <hi>Graſerus</hi> deſcribing the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> ſaith, he is one, <hi>Qui im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietati ſuae Dei nomen pretendit,</hi> vvhich ſhall pretend the Name of God in all his impieties. Add to this, 1. The number of Sycophants and flatterers every vvhere (eſpecially Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) vvho cry up the oppreſſours of the Nation as the only men for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, mercy, piety, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. By how much the crying ſins of the Nation are vvitneſſed againſt, the more do men riſe and grow vvorſe and vvorſe in the practice of them. Now vvhat do theſe things preſage, but that God is ready <hi>to lay the axe to the root of the tree? Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? and ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> Jer. 5.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is uſually Gods dealing with his people (as I ſaid before) vvhen he draws out their hearts to an earneſt ſeeking of him, to grant them vvhat they ask. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He was the Spirits
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135122:41"/>priſoner,</hi> Act. 20.22. The like is the caſe now of many pretious Saints: <hi>Such a powerful-commanding impulſe</hi> they find upon their Spirits, that they <hi>cannot reſt day nor night,</hi> but muſt be ſighing and groaning, that the Lord vvould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly make this <hi>ſecond ſhaking,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move unrighteous perſons and things, and make the Nation happy and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, by eſtabliſhing truth and juſtice in the midſt of it. I know theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted (by the <hi>thriving party) madmen, giddy-heads, fantaſticks, the greateſt fools of the time:</hi> But God ere long will put the <hi>Queſtion</hi> out of queſtion; that is, vvhether thoſe vvho prayed againſt oppreſſours, and to have Magiſtrates and Judges as at the firſt, did well, and therein pleaſed God; or ſuch as did flatter them, and vvould have them ſtill continue, to the end they might ſerve themſelves upon them.</p>
            <p>And as the Spirit puts a <hi>holy force</hi> upon them to pray <hi>continually,</hi> ſo they have many weighty encouragements not to faint.</p>
            <p>For 1. It is generally beleeved by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135122:42"/>this <hi>Generation of Seekers,</hi> That <hi>England</hi> will never be beautiful and lovely, but rather her preſent blackneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity increaſe, untill thoſe be <hi>ſhaken,</hi> who have made her moſt unlovely; yea, <hi>vile</hi> in the ſight of the vvorld.</p>
            <p>Neither 2. will there be any <hi>State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaking</hi> in other Nations, as to the cutting off of Tyrants, and planting righteouſneſs among them, until ſome eminent vvork be done here firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a righteous ſetling of a good Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is their beleef, That the Lord ere long vvill ſo honour a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Governours here eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, as they ſhall be very uſeful and inſtrumental to carry on his great vvork in the World; that is, deſtroy <hi>Babylon,</hi> bring down the Enemies of Chriſt under his feet, promote righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs every vvhere; yea, and help the Lords <hi>Ancient people</hi> when their day ſhall come.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They are perſwaded, The Lord <hi>will not be turned from the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his anger, and intreated for the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135122:42"/>Land, until there be a publick check given to the late Apostacie by the Repreſentatives of the people. They hanged</hi> Haman, <hi>&amp;c. Then was the Kings wrath pacified,</hi> Eſth. 7.10. <hi>So they took up Jonah and caſt him forth into the ſea, and the ſea ceaſed from her ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,</hi> Jon. 1.15.</p>
            <p>If vve ſee a man vvhet and ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a tool, vve conclude he intends to do ſomething vvith it: as the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of <hi>ſhaking the Earth yet once more,</hi> Heb. 12. ſo I think the Lord is now preparing <hi>Inſtruments</hi> for it. The vvork is ſuch, as it needs no fine tools; <hi>rough tools</hi> vvill ſerve well enough, eſpecially being to be us'd by ſo ſtrong &amp; powerful an hand: when God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zecharie</hi> the <hi>Horns,</hi> he ſhewed him the <hi>Carpenters</hi> too, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in a little cloud</hi> ſaw abundance of rain. Methinks in this <hi>National cloud</hi> I ſee both rain and hail; <hi>Rain</hi> for the refreſhing of the Earth, after more then 3 <hi>years and an half</hi> drought. What thinkſt thou, <hi>Reader,</hi> would it not be a pleaſant ſight, to ſee our Rights and Priviledges again to <hi>ſpring:</hi> it is now
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135122:43"/>towards the <hi>Spring,</hi> and who knows, but we may have a GOOD SPRING of it; yea, and a <hi>fruitful Summer</hi> too? I mean, ſuch proviſion and care taken, as to have no more ſuch <hi>deſtroying win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (as we have had of late) by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too much truſt in the hands of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful men.</p>
            <p>Again, methinks I ſee in this <hi>cloud</hi> ſome <hi>hail;</hi> and why not that Propheſie here to be fulfilled, <hi>Judgment alſo will I lay to the line, and righteouſneſs to the plummet; AND THE HAIL SHALL SWEEP AWAY THE REFUGE OF LIES, and the waters ſhall overflow the hiding place,</hi> Iſa. 28.17. But I ſhall refer the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to the REASONS which he ſhall find in the cloſe of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have great hope that the Nation will reap much good by this preſent <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our 2. Argument is, <hi>If this preſent Government be that State-Apoſtacie of which</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaks,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c. Then is the ſhaking of it intended in this Text. But the firſt is true: Therefore the ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:135122:43"/>
            <p> This I ſhall take for granted (for I am ſure no underſtanding Chriſtian will deny me it) that the <hi>ſhaking of the two grand-Apoſtacies fore-told in Scripture, are certainly meant in</hi> Heb. 12.27. And therefore leaving that part of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which is vvithout diſpute; I ſhall endeavour to prove the other <hi>Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That there ſhould be in <hi>Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, two notorious Apoſtacies,</hi> is evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed in Scripture. The firſt in <hi>the later days;</hi> and this in <hi>Doctrine;</hi> that is, <hi>a departure from the faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1, 2. 2 Theſ. 2.3. 2 Pet. 2.1, 2. Act. 20.30. The <hi>ſecond Apoſtacie, in the last days,</hi> and this to be in <hi>practiſe;</hi> that is, a corrupt life or converſation: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the <hi>firſt Apostacie</hi> was a <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and had a HEAD ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to it, and Laws made ſutable to that <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> Rev. 16.10. <hi>and</hi> 13.2. So the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie is to be a State, a <hi>Body,</hi> or <hi>Dominion,</hi> Dan. 7.11, 26. and to have a <hi>Head</hi> or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector ſet over it, and ſuch Laws de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135122:44"/>as may beſt fit the intereſt of the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Body:</hi> and ſo much lies plainly in the Text; <hi>Perillous days ſhall come;</hi> intimating a power in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie,</hi> to act wickedneſs by a Law, in ſpight of all oppoſition, ſo long as the Apoſtacie ſhould continue: for had it not been ſo, it could not have been <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous days,</hi> as the Text holds forth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>first</hi> Apoſtacie had its riſe in the Church, occaſioned through the covetouſneſs, pride, ſelf-ſeeking, Covenant-breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of profeſſors, 2 Pet. 2.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.3. So the <hi>ſecond preſent</hi> Apoſtacie, had its riſe in the Church, and among eminent Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Religion; and the Cauſe of it the very ſame mentioned before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were <hi>lovers of themſelves, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, proud,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3. obſerve then, this Apoſtacie cannot be made by <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It muſt riſe in the Church, and among Profeſſors of Religion, who have the right worſhip of God, in <hi>form</hi> at leaſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As they gave to the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>first</hi> Apoſtacie all power, and to do
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135122:44"/>what he would, being above all, and to be obeyed of all, and not ſubject to any Council, power, or Authority on Earth; ſo the Head of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was <hi>Dominus omnium temporalium,</hi> Lord of every mans goods, he might do what he would, <hi>ſupra jus, contra jus, &amp; extra jus,</hi> above Law, againſt Law, and without Law; he was allowed to be above the people in their <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> and to call Parliaments when he pleas'd, and to break them as oft as he would.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Upon the <hi>Head of the first</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, is <hi>characterized</hi> the <hi>number of the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13.18. VICARIUS DEI GENERALIS IN TERRIS; which according to the numeral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is, 666. The very ſame <hi>number</hi> is on the head of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie, DUX GENERALIS ET PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TECTOR; that is, 666. <hi>Here is wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Let him that hath understanding, count the number of the Beaſt, for it is the number of a man, and his number is ſix hundred threeſcore and ſix,</hi> Rev. 13.18. The Engliſh of the firſt is, <hi>Gods Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135122:45"/>on Earth;</hi> the other, <hi>Captain General and Protector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It is a wonderful thing to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when the <hi>Heathen Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> were ſubdued, the Idols of the Gentiles thrown down, Perſecution taken off from the Church, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty granted unto tender Conſciences in the exerciſe of Religion; that juſt then, <hi>the Let ſhould be taken out of the way,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.7. and the <hi>firſt</hi> Apoſtacie riſe in the Chriſtian Church. Who would have thought when the Kings head was taken off, and with it that form of Government; When the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> were put down, with <hi>Altars, Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Service-Book, Ceremonies,</hi> and other <hi>Popiſh-Idols;</hi> Perſecution ſtopt, and liberty given to tender Conſciences: I ſay, who would have thought that Profeſſors of Religion (yea, thoſe who had the greateſt ſhare and advantage in ſuch mercies) would have brought forth inſtead of grapes, the wild-grapes of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie? as if there had been no time for them, till juſt then, to have ſhewed their hypocriſie,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135122:45"/>falſhood, pride, covetouſneſs, treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But beſides the parallel between the two <hi>State-Apostacies,</hi> that we have the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie at this time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us appears thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We ſee plainly, though they left <hi>the power of godlineſs,</hi> and became <hi>ſelf-ſeekers, covetous, proud, traytors, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breakers;</hi> yet they held faſt the form, or outſide of Religion: as men that have ſores and ulcers upon their bodies, throw not away their clothes, but keep them on for <hi>covering.</hi> And here the <hi>Reader</hi> is to obſerve, that this <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie cannot rightly be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to any but to Profeſſors of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; for ſuch as have neither power nor form of godlineſs, cannot be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with it; they may be among the Apoſtates and helpers of the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, but not proper members.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be underſtood that the <hi>men</hi> in the Text ſaid to be <hi>lovers of themſelves, covetuos, proud,</hi> &amp;c. did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſeem otherwiſe, and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe very vices and corruptions in others; for elſe it could not have been
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135122:46"/>an <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> or falling from righteous Principles, to a ſcandalous and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt walking. Now who more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> for their miſcarriages whilſt they ſtood, then thoſe men, whoſe miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages ſince, have been far worſe in the very ſame particulars wherein the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were charged. I need not give inſtances; it is poſſible this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may have occaſion to remember the <hi>old Court</hi> and <hi>the new;</hi> and the <hi>old Biſhops</hi> and <hi>the new Biſhops.</hi> If they do, there is hope then, that the greateſt grievances of the Nation will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and the Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reſtored.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In that way which Apoſtates ſeek to cover their Apoſtacie, doth the Lord diſcover both it and them. What is the way they take to have their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacie hid, and not known? it is by taking up a <hi>form of Godlineſs.</hi> And how doth the <hi>Lord</hi> unmask them, and make their Apoſtacie known? by that <hi>form</hi> of Godlineſs which they have taken up. And the truth is, were theſe men
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135122:46"/>more <hi>ſelf-ſeeking, covetous, proud,</hi> &amp;c. then they are, yet this alone would not prove them to be the <hi>later</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, unleſs with thoſe vices and ſins they had alſo a <hi>form of godlineſs;</hi> that is, did preach, pray, faſt, and made a great noiſe and ſhew of the outſide of Religion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I know no better way for a man to have ſatisfaction in this thing, then firſt to conſider what the ſins are ſet down in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. foretold ſhould be in the <hi>later State-Apoſtacie,</hi> and then to look about him, and ſee whether they are not all, and every one of them to be ſeen, as viſibly and plainly as was the leproſie in <hi>Gehazi</hi>'s forehead. If the <hi>Reader</hi> do deſire more to inform himſelf in this matter, I ſhall refer him to a <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> intituled <hi>The time of the End,</hi> at <hi>pag.</hi> 36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where all the <hi>Characters of the laſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacie</hi> are fully opened.</p>
            <p>Having ſpoken of the <hi>first and ſecond ſhaking of the Earth,</hi> I come now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my thoughts concerning the manner of the <hi>ſecond ſhaking</hi> (for of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135122:47"/>the firſt I have ſpoken) and by whom the work will be done. And laſtly, my Reaſons, wherefore I think the time of this <hi>later ſhaking</hi> is nigh. The Scripture which I ſhall a little treat of, is in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. <hi>And the ſame hour was there a great Earth-quake, and the tenth part of the Citie fell, and in the Earth-quake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand; and the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have thought ſometimes, that this <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> and the powring out of the <hi>first vial,</hi> had contemporized, and been all one thing; but ſeriouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving again the places, it ſeems to me, that this <hi>Earth-quake</hi> will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any vial is powred out, and ſhall be a fore-runner (as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was to Chriſt) that is, prepare or make way for the <hi>Vials.</hi> About the time of this <hi>Earth-quake (in the ſame hour,</hi> ſaith the Text) <hi>the witneſſes aſcend up to Heaven in a Cloud.</hi> If by the <hi>witneſſes</hi> here, we underſtand <hi>fifth-Monarchy-men,</hi> and their work to be about the more pure and ſpiritual part of the <hi>fifth Kingdom,</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:135122:47"/>I conceive then, theſe do remain in Heaven, or the <hi>Temple,</hi> Rev. 15.6. (for I take it to be one thing) until the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> be made by the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths</hi>-men, as making way for the <hi>ſeven laſt plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire I may not be miſtaken in mentioning <hi>fifth Monarchy-men</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth-men</hi> diſtinct; I do it not as if they were not one people, and their work all one in reſpect of pulling down and building up; but in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the manner and way, how theſe things ſhall be done. The <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> will be (as I ſaid) before the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,</hi> for theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Howſoever there are many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences among the Lords people, as what is <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet in this they are all ſatisfied, and do unanimouſly accord, <hi>That all heavy burdens ſhould be broken, Tyrants (new as well as old) removed, the juſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the people reſtored, Righteouſneſs ſetled in the Nation, and the good old Cauſe up again, conquering and to conquer.</hi> Now as the Lord in theſe things hath made
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135122:48"/>his people of one mind, ſo he will have them joyn together in the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them: for things farther off (as about the <hi>vials</hi>) they ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have light in them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.1. and accord in the work, when the time coms to put them in execution. <hi>Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing,</hi> Phil. 3.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſeems to me, that this <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> will be before the <hi>Vials;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> is under <hi>the ſecond wo,</hi> Rev. 11.13, 14. but all the <hi>vials</hi> (as I conceive) fall under the <hi>third wo</hi> (which is the laſt) &amp; therefore are ſaid to be <hi>the ſeven laſt plagues,</hi> Rev. 15.1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Scriptures be heeded which treat of the <hi>fifth Kingdom,</hi> it will appear, that the <hi>great work</hi> which the Lord will bring to paſs for his <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Zion in the laſt days,</hi> will begin at <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs among men;</hi> that is, to deſtroy oppreſſion and Tyranny in every kind; all corrupt Laws, and wicked Orders and Cuſtoms, and to have things ſo ſetled, as every man may have his due
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135122:48"/>and juſt Rights: <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall be the girdle of his loins, and faithfulneſs the girdle of his reins,</hi> Iſa. 11.5. <hi>A ſcepter of righteouſneſs is the ſcepter of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> Heb. 1.6. There is a <hi>voice of many waters,</hi> before the <hi>voice of a great thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> Rev. 14.2. <hi>Waters</hi> are below, <hi>thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> above; the work begins below at <hi>the waters:</hi> let us therefore take heed, that we miſs not the proper work of the day, in not beginning where we ſhould.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As God is a God of <hi>order,</hi> not <hi>of confuſion;</hi> ſo I think the <hi>great work of the times</hi> will be carried on in a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and comly order. It is ſaid, <hi>The stone was cut out of the mountain,</hi> Dan. 2.45. Obſerve, it is CUT; ſo that it is not without <hi>form,</hi> it hath ſome comlineſs, faſhion, and order in it. I ſee no obſtruction, why all that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning the execution of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> or what is to be done by Saints as Saints (of publick concernment) till Chriſt perſonally appear, but may very well ſtand with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135122:49"/>good order. For example: Is it not poſſible that a Government may be rightly eſtabliſhed, and ſuch Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours choſen, as the tendereſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may ſafely act under it?</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>The ten horns ſhall hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16. I do underſtand this of a State or Government (let it be part of the <hi>fifth Kingdom</hi>) and the meaning to be this: when the <hi>Lamb</hi> hath overcome any Nation, there ſhall be that <hi>Government</hi> erected, and ſuch <hi>Governours</hi> ſet up, who will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim open war againſt <hi>the great whore,</hi> and raiſe up forces to reward her dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the blood ſhe had ſhed, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominable wickedneſs. This being ſo, it muſt needs follow, that the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> will be before the <hi>vials;</hi> for it is not to be imagined that the <hi>Repreſentatives of a Nation,</hi> if they are wiſe and ſober, will meddle with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> abroad, untill they have made a good Reformation, and things well
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135122:49"/>ſetled at home.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If God have a voice in humane affairs, and to be hearkned to and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, then I conceive this <hi>Earth-quake</hi> will be next; that is, a purging out of the <hi>droſs</hi> and <hi>filthineſs</hi> amongſt us, that <hi>righteouſneſs may dwell in the Land;</hi> this indeed we may now expect: for the harveſt of the <hi>later Apoſtacie</hi> is ripe, and the Lord ſeems to have prepared ſome <hi>ſharp ſickles</hi> for the cutting down of it. But for any other publick work at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I do not ſee the like fitneſs either in things or perſons.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken the more of this, to the end, that whilſt we are looking at things further off, we do not forget our duty and work in things neerer home. I have read ſomewhere of an <hi>Admiral,</hi> when he ſhould have gone preſently in with the reſt of the fleet to fight the Enemy, he turned aſide and wheel'd about ſo far, that he never came in, to give a ſtroke. If we take not heed, our <hi>darling conceits</hi> will turn us aſide, and cauſe us to wheel off from
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135122:50"/>the <hi>fight, i. e.</hi> our preſent <hi>Generation</hi>-work. If ſo, whoſoever the Lord ſhall honour in following him to the Battle and for his faithfulneſs in it, we for our parts can expect nothing but ſhame and diſhonour.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is meant by the</hi> Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake <hi>in the Text?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Repreſentatives of the people aſſembled in Parliament, by whom the <hi>later State</hi>-Apoſtacie ſhall be put down. So I take it. But,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I do not reſtrain this <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake</hi> to our <hi>Nation:</hi> I have ſhewed before, that one Propheſie may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten fulfilled. Thus, for ought I ſee to the contrary, the <hi>ſlaying of the witneſſes,</hi> and their <hi>riſing,</hi> may be done over and over; one while in one Country, and ſometimes in another, in reſpect of time, perſons, and place. But what peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoever are left out of theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, we are not. For there is none of them (which concern the <hi>Gentile Saints</hi> in the laſt times) but they will have ſome accompliſhment here; yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135122:50"/>of them more eminently here then elſewhere, eſpecially at firſt. But of this I have ſpoken before.</p>
            <p>Neither 2. do I fix any time when this <hi>Earth-quake</hi> ſhall be. For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I have ſtrong perſwaſions that <hi>the work will begin at the ſitting of this preſent Parliament;</hi> yet I am not ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the Lord will honour them in ſo noble and glorious a Cauſe for their poor country, as I am confident he will do it by others, if they neglect their duty. <hi>For the needy ſhall not always be forgotten; the expectation of the poor ſhall not periſh for ever,</hi> Pſal. 9.18.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But why is the laying aſide of the preſent</hi> State-Apoſtacie, <hi>and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nation to a</hi> Common-wealth <hi>again, ſet forth by an</hi> Earth-quake?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe in all likelihood before it be over, it will make a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and terrible ſhaking: <hi>Wo, wo, wo, to the inhabitants of the three Nations;</hi> who knows but this <hi>Earth-quake</hi> will raze the foundation of our <hi>new Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> reach the <hi>Tryers, Lawyers, Seſſers, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135122:51"/>Exciſe-men, Custome-houſe-men, Corporations,</hi> &amp;c. in a word, all the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring vermine</hi> in the Land, ſuch as have taken away mens goods contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſhew when the Lord will raiſe up inſtruments againſt this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie, they ſhall prevail, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all <hi>Ahitophels</hi> and <hi>Machiavels,</hi> in ſpight of Hell and all powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It is an <hi>Earth-quake: Stand now with thine inchantments, and with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy ſorceries, wherein thou haſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured from thy youth; if ſo be thou ſhalt be able to profit, if ſo be thou mayest prevail. Let now the Aſtrologers, the Star-gazers, the Monthly-Prognoſticators stand up, aad ſave thee from theſe things that ſhall come upon thee,</hi> Iſa. 47.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It may denote the cauſe of the <hi>ſhaking;</hi> that this State-Apoſtacie is removed, it is, that oppreſſion and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny may ceaſe, and all people have their rights. Now howſoever this be a good work, and ought to be done, yet it riſeth no higher then <hi>Earth,</hi> and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135122:51"/>therefore fitly called an <hi>Earth-quake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the <hi>infamous memory</hi> of this <hi>laſt</hi> Apoſtacie, and the <hi>happy downfall</hi> of it may continue to all <hi>future Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> Such deſolations and ruines as formerly were made by <hi>Earth-quakes,</hi> we find them recorded in Hiſtories both Divine and Humane, <hi>Amos</hi> 1.1. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5. to the end that ſuch things might not be forgotten. It is true, many <hi>National Earth-quakes</hi> hath this <hi>Iſland</hi> ſuffered, <hi>viz.</hi> by the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes, Normans,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides ſeveral <hi>Earth-quakes</hi> among our ſelves, by <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Civil Wars.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, I am very confident, that the memory of none of them will ſo long laſt, as the rembrance of this <hi>preſent</hi> Apoſtacie, and that SEASONABLE GOOD-EARTH-QUAKE, which not only ſhaked it, but ſwallowed it up. My Reaſon is, becauſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Gods great Name, the Cauſe of Religion, and the intereſt of Chriſt and his people, have more ſuffered by this <hi>preſent</hi> Apoſtacie in <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135122:52"/>yeers,</hi> then ever they ſuffered under the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes, Normans,</hi> put them all together, and all their time too: Some report the <hi>prints</hi> of <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohs Charriot-wheels</hi> did remain in the ſand of the ſhore at the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> and was to be ſeen many hundred yeers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I ſhall not ſtand to the truth of that: but this is a truth, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide by it, <hi>That the print of this</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie <hi>is ſo deep in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, made by ſelf-ſeeking, covetouſneſs, hypocriſie, Covenant-breaking, treachery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that it will remain to be ſeen many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. To ſhew, that the Apoſtacie was ſuch a BURDEN as the Earth could no longer bear it, but muſt needs <hi>quake</hi> under it, and ſo ſhake it out. <hi>The land is defiled, therefore do I viſit the iniquity thereof upon it, and the land it ſelf vomiteth out her inhabitants,</hi> Lev. 18.25. <hi>The earth is utterly broken down, the Earth is clean diſſolved, the Earth is removed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. The Earth ſhall reel to and fro like a drunkard, and ſhall be removed like
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135122:52"/>a cottage. The tranſgreſſion of it ſhall be heavy upon it, and it ſhall fall and not riſe again,</hi> Iſa. 24.19, 20.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To anſwer an ancient Type in <hi>the old Teſtament:</hi> For in the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> was clearly ſhadowed out the <hi>laſt</hi> Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Amongſt many other parallels which might be noted, take theſe few:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Rebellion</hi> was made a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after the Lord had given a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful deliverance to his Church, and when they ſhould have paſſed over <hi>Jordan</hi> to the <hi>Promiſed Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The occaſion of it was ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and <hi>love of pre-eminence</hi> in ſome perſons, not contented with that <hi>form of Government</hi> which the Lord a little before had appointed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Howſoever the Action was wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, (no leſs then <hi>high Treaſon</hi>) yet the chief Authors of it are ſaid to be <hi>famous in the Congregation, and men of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That this Apoſtacie might the more effectually be carried on, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:135122:53"/>and <hi>Freedom</hi> of the people was pretended: and that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron had taken too much upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Howſoever few at firſt had a hand in this <hi>Rebellion</hi> (by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text it ſeems to be only <hi>Korah</hi>) yet thorow the hypocriſie and falſhood of theſe few, many afterwards were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The Earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed them up.</hi> An <hi>Earth-quake</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; yet a juſt reward for ſuch Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Reader, The <hi>Sentence</hi> is left to thee, only be honeſt; did not this Apoſtacie riſe aſſoon as the Lord had delivered us out of the hands of our Enemies? and when in duty and Conſcience we ſhould have gone forward in his work? And was it not through the baſe pride of ſome men (to have all power in their own hands) that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation was changed from a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> (which the Lord had own'd and bleſt) to a THING which we cannot tell what it is? Again,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135122:53"/>though by <hi>three Acts of Parliament it was made Treaſon, to promote any perſon to be King or Chief Magiſtrate of</hi> England <hi>or</hi> Ireland, <hi>without conſent of Parliament:</hi> Yet this was done; But by whom? <hi>Men famous in the Congregation, and of great renown.</hi> And that they might the more prevail in their Rebellion, was not Liberty promiſed, and taking off the grievances of the People? Is not this very true likewiſe, that this <hi>State-Apoſtacie</hi> was firſt ſet on foot by a few (ſome ſay ſeven or eight, but more probably it was but one) yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Multitudes, multitudes</hi> fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſin and ſnare? In concluſion then, wherein agrees not the <hi>Anti-type</hi> with the <hi>Type,</hi> but that the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> is not executed upon the <hi>later Rebellion? Conſider of it, take advice, and ſpeak your minds,</hi> Judg. 19.30.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>It is ſaid in the Text,</hi> The tenth part of the City fell, and in the Earth-quake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand, <hi>&amp;c. What is meant by it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As there are <hi>two Apoſtacies</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:135122:54"/>foretold in Scripture; ſo I find <hi>two Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> Firſt, the GREAT CITY; ſignifying, <hi>the whole Dominion and juriſdiction of the Papal Beaſt;</hi> that is, all States and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, Civil and Religious, under the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> and acknowledging the Pope <hi>Head</hi> of the Church. And note, when ever this <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>State</hi> is meant by the word <hi>City,</hi> it is always expreſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>That great City,</hi> Rev. 11.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.8. <hi>and</hi> 16.19. <hi>and</hi> 17.18. <hi>and</hi> 18.10, 16, 18, 19. <hi>and</hi> 21.10. By which we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>firſt</hi> Apoſtacie: As for the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie, is called a City likewiſe; but the word GREAT is left out, and there is great Reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>For 1. This <hi>later</hi> Apoſtacie ſhall not be ſo large as the <hi>former,</hi> in ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf over all peoples and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Tongues; <hi>All the world won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred after the first Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither 2. ſhall the <hi>later</hi> Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie have that honour and homage done
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135122:54"/>to it, as had the <hi>former: For the Kings of the Earth ſhall give their Kingdoms unto the first Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 17.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>firſt</hi> Apoſtacie is to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue 1260 <hi>years,</hi> but the <hi>later</hi> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>three yeers and an half,</hi> till the Lord doth begin to ſtrike it with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. So that the word GREAT, ſeems to be left out here, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the <hi>two Cities,</hi> or <hi>two</hi> Apoſtacies; and this in the Text is to be underſtood of the <hi>later State</hi>-Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie. Moreover, we have ſome light here how to underſtand that place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. where it is ſaid of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <hi>their dead bodies ſhall lie in the ſtreet of the great City:</hi> it is well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by many, that the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (<hi>i. e. a broad</hi> or <hi>ſpatious place</hi>) doth not ſignifie <hi>any place, Market-place,</hi> or <hi>broad place</hi> within the walls of the <hi>great City;</hi> but it is without the <hi>great City,</hi> as no part of the building. Hence we may conclude two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>two Witneſſes</hi> are not ſlain (in their <hi>Teſtimony</hi>) by any <hi>Civil Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:135122:55"/>that hold the Pope <hi>Head of the Church;</hi> neither lie their <hi>dead bodies</hi> in any Country formally ſubject to the <hi>See of Rome.</hi> For their <hi>ſlaying and lying dead</hi> muſt be without the walls of the <hi>great City.</hi> Indeed the blood of the Martyrs will be charged upon the <hi>firſt</hi> Apoſtacie; but the <hi>ſlaying of the witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> upon the <hi>ſecond</hi> Apoſtacie. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let <hi>Church-Members</hi> and <hi>Church-Officers,</hi> and other <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> look to it. For to ſpeak ſoberly and in the fear of God, this is my opinion (and I think grounded upon Scripture and practice) <hi>The blood of the witneſſes will be required at their hands:</hi> for never had <hi>the bottomleſs Beaſt</hi> murdred ſo bleſſed a Cauſe, and ſo glorious a Teſtimony for Chriſt and his Kingdom (as was in this Nation) had they ſtood faithful to the <hi>good old Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Though the <hi>Power</hi> by which the <hi>witneſſes</hi> are ſlain, is not from the <hi>great City,</hi> yet it is for it; that is, it doth more ſtrengthen and ſupport the <hi>great whore</hi> then any State or Government
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135122:55"/>properly the <hi>whores.</hi> Where lies now the <hi>ſtop,</hi> that the Lords work goes not forward, to remove oppreſſions and heavie burdens, and to eſtabliſh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs among men? Not in <hi>Rome, Spain, Germany, France;</hi> the <hi>ſtop</hi> is neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er home: remove this Apoſtacie, and you ſhall ſoon ſee the <hi>good Cauſe</hi> reviv'd again, and the hearts of all good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reviv'd with it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The tenth part of the City fell, and the remnant gave glory to God;</hi> this cannot be meant of the <hi>great City,</hi> for that <hi>ſinks</hi> (every whit) <hi>like a great milstone to the bottom of the Sea:</hi> Beſides, I do not read of any <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving glory to God</hi> in the <hi>great City</hi> when her plagues are upon her. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary (it is expreſly ſaid) <hi>they repented not, to give glory to God, but blaſphemed the God of Heaven becauſe of their pains and their ſores,</hi> Rev. 16.9, 11. Now the Reaſon is, becauſe the Lord will bring his people out of the <hi>great City Babylon,</hi> (as he did <hi>Lot</hi> from <hi>Sodom</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he burns her to aſhes. I will
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135122:56"/>not ſay, among that huge heap of chaff, there will be no corn; yet I think, if any of Gods elect ſhall periſh (as to the outward man) in that common deſtruction; they will be very few, yea, in thoſe few, no repenting and giving glory to God, viſibly will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.6.</p>
            <p>But the Caſe here is otherwiſe: for howſoever the whole Apoſtacie will fall, yet in the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> all will not be ſlain that are found in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie. When <hi>Abſalom</hi> made that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Rebellion againſt his father, it is ſaid, <hi>two hundred followed him in the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of their hearts, and knew not any thing,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.11. that is, they were ignorant of the wicked plot he had in hand; namely, under pretence of devotion and conſcience to deſtroy his own father, and make himſelf king or <hi>Chief Magiſtrate.</hi> No doubt many <hi>two hundreds,</hi> thouſands, I may ſay, through the diſſimulation and lying of their Leaders and Teachers, have fallen in with the Apoſtacie, ſimply
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135122:56"/>and ignorantly, knew nothing of their deſign, that is, how under a cloke of Religion, and the ſafety of the <hi>godly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> the <hi>mother Commonwealth</hi> was to be murthered, and an <hi>Abſalom-like intereſt</hi> to be ſet up. Therefore by the <hi>Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> here, I underſtand theſe <hi>ignorant and ſimple ones;</hi> not the OLD SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENT, the ſeducers and ringlead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who thought they had done their Country and themſelves good ſervice, when they ſought to deſtroy the lives and Liberties of the people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>In the Earthquake was ſlain of men</hi> 7000. the Greek hath <hi>names of men;</hi> meaning, <hi>men of note, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, famous,</hi> Gen. 6.4. contrary hereto, is <hi>men without Name,</hi> Job 30.8. alluding to <hi>the Rebellion of Korah,</hi> &amp;c. Num. 16.2. &amp; two things ſeem to be held forth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Earth-quake</hi> (that is, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the people</hi>) ſhall be <hi>men of courage,</hi> and of publick ſpirits, ſuch as ſhall have <hi>Lion-like hearts,</hi> fear no mans face, nor reſpect any mans perſon; but will cut down <hi>Cedars,</hi> aſſoon as <hi>ſhrubs,</hi> if there be cauſe for it. Indeed no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135122:57"/>in the world formerly have been more honoured then the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for men of reſolution, and of high and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirits, in ſtanding up for their freedom and Rights, againſt intruſion and uſurpation of all ſorts and ſizes. But, <hi>How is the faithful City become an harlot? it was full of judgment, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lodged in it, but now murderers. Thy ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is become droſs, thy wine mixt with water. Thy Princes are rebellious, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of theeves; every one loveth gifts, and follow after reward; they judge not the fatherleſs, neither doth the cauſe of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow come unto them,</hi> Iſa. 1.21, 22, 23. Oh! that it ſhould be ſaid, ICHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BOD, <hi>The glory is departed from En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> For have not men of late ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves to be of low, baſe, and ſervile ſpirits, in preferring their own particular intereſt, before the publick good of the Nation? And in ſtead of contending for our <hi>Birth-right</hi> (which but a little before was recovered with the Blood and Treaſure of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to give it up (or rather ſold it) <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau-like, for a meſs of Pottage?</hi> But God
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135122:57"/>will raiſe up a better Generation of men (and why may not we hope it is now?) who will recover the Glory of the Engliſh nation again, by exalting truth and righteouſneſs among us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>names of men,</hi> is not meant the <hi>old names of note, renown, and famous</hi> in the days of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops;</hi> for they concern not the <hi>later Apoſtacie:</hi> but the <hi>new names;</hi> that is, <hi>Lords, Knights, Eſquires,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the last edition.</hi> Thoſe who were poor the other day, and have made their families great by hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and lies, and betraying their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, muſt expect to fall by this <hi>Earth-quake.</hi> For the number <hi>ſeven thouſand,</hi> it is probable before the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> be done, not fewer will be ſhaken; for it muſt go round the Nation, and follow the <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> from end to end. And I hope the appearance of it will be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly; we are waiting for it, and praying for it. <hi>So come Lord Jeſus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="reasons">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:135122:58"/>
               <head>Reaſons, Why it may be hoped, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Parliament</hi> will begin the <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> or <hi>Second Shaking</hi> of the <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the late experience we have had of ſome mens unfaithfulneſs and falſhood, and ſeriouſly weighing what a <hi>pitiful choice</hi> ſome have made: this could not but altogether diſcourage me of <hi>Hope,</hi> were not my eyes upon the <hi>Mighty Creator,</hi> and ſo better bottom'd, then to put confidence in man. What my <hi>Reaſons</hi> are, I ſhall here ſet down, and ſo leave it to the <hi>Readers</hi> judgment, <hi>Whether from ſuch grounds, there may not be</hi> Hope <hi>of reviving the</hi> Good old Cauſe <hi>by this</hi> Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. The Lord taking away that HEAD-STOP lately from us, ſeems to ſpeak much good in it to all <hi>Lovers of Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Nation. <hi>Ariſe, and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Iſrael; for they are dead which ſought the young childs life,</hi> Mat. 2.20. What otherwiſe was the Lord voice in that <hi>Signal Providence,</hi> but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:135122:58"/>if he ſhould ſay to the Repreſentatives of the People, <hi>Ariſe, take the Mother Commonwealth, and her young child,</hi> i. e. <hi>her Rights, Priviledges,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and go into London:</hi> i. e. <hi>let things be ſetled and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabliſhed as before: for they are dead which ſought to devour Mother and Child, ſo that there is no fear in returning to the good old work and Cauſe again. Thou bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the heads of Leviathan in peeces, &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him to be meat to the people inhabiting the wilderneſs,</hi> Pſal. 74.14. The meaning is, Gods revenging hand upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> was to nouriſh and ſtrengthen <hi>Iſrael</hi> afterward; as to beleeve the Lord would not have done that great thing for them, had he not meant to bring them to the <hi>Promiſed Land.</hi> Truly, that <hi>Stroak</hi> to me <hi>hath been meat in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and I cannot but think, as it was the Lords doing, ſo it was done, that the three Nations might the ſooner enjoy their juſt Rights again.</p>
               <p>It is the opinion of many, that in <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> (as to their Kingdoms) is ſhadowed out two <hi>States</hi> to be in the laſt days: when <hi>Saul</hi> was dead (the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135122:59"/>great <hi>Block</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> way) it is ſaid, <hi>Abner the ſon of Ner, Captain of Sauls hoſt, took Iſhboſheth the ſon of Saul, and made him King,</hi> 2 Sam. 2.8, 9. Note three things in this buſineſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What <hi>Abner</hi> did herein, was contrary to his light; for he knew well enough, that God had appointed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man to reign; only his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>houſe of Saul</hi> (for he was <hi>Sauls</hi> unkle) and his own baſe intereſt, made him do what he did againſt knowledge and conſcience, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It appears by the Text, that this <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> (which is by interpretation A MAN OF SHAME, and his end proved ſo) was a fellow of a low, fearful, and weak ſpirit, not like his father <hi>Saul,</hi> neither for valour nor po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie; meerly ſet to ſerve a <hi>Court-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> and that a company of corrupt men might ſerve themſelves upon him, as not liking <hi>David</hi> and his way; for they knew <hi>David</hi> was a man more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and conſcientious, then to ſuffer ſuch <hi>locuſts</hi> &amp; <hi>caterpillars</hi> to ſpoil &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135122:59"/>the Commonwealth, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not only in the end is this <hi>mock-King</hi> left of his RAISERS, but hath his head taken off by two of his own Captains; a juſt reward for him, and for all ſuch who will take upon them the power and Government of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt the manifeſt appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. What may be in the application, time will ſhew. In the mean time, take notice, if the time be come, <hi>That the Kingdoms of this world are to be the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 11.15. and that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is to be exalted in the Nations; then none of the <hi>Houſe of Saul</hi> ſhall long reign, but the <hi>Houſe of David</hi> will grow ſtronger and ſtronger, and carry it in ſpight of all oppoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Methinks it cannot be, but there is a <hi>wheel in the wheel,</hi> and the Lords hand moving to the <hi>ſhaking the Earth the ſecond time;</hi> in that I ſee of late a ſpirit of prayer and ſupplication poured out upon many choice Chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are enabled to wreſtle with the Lord in prayer day and night for the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135122:60"/>publick good of the Nation, more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly then they did before. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for theſe <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five yeers,</hi> that it hath not been upon the hearts of the faithful, to expect any good from <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments;</hi> and therefore moſt of their praying hath been (and no doubt by the Holy Spirit led thereto) that the Lord would blaſt them, and break them to peeces, that the ſtout-hearted might be ſpoiled, and none of the men of might find their hands. But I find it otherwiſe now; for the Lord of late hath put it upon their hearts with much weight, to be dayly groaning at the throne of Grace, that all thoſe who like good <hi>Nehemiah, Come to ſeek the welfare of the children of Iſrael, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the breaches of the Commonwealth, may through God do valiantly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No doubt, honeſt <hi>Huſhai</hi> proſpered the better, when he ſought to fruſtrate the wicked counſel of <hi>Ahitophel,</hi> that he had <hi>Davids</hi> prayers for him and with him. <hi>And David ſaid, O Lord, I pray thee turn the counſel of Ahitophel to fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.31. Let ſuch know,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135122:60"/>who are our <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s at this time, and ſeek to break the deſigns of <hi>Ahitophels,</hi> and all ſuch as would keep up a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt intereſt againſt the publick good of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> there are many tears and prayers poured out for them. And I am confident, they will experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the fruit and benefit of them all along upon their endeavours for the righteous Cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. I have the more <hi>ground of hope,</hi> conſidering ſome perſons now <hi>ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> were not only <hi>Members of the long Parliament,</hi> and ſought to extirpate things that ſtood in the way of a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Reformation; but have not ſince warped and deflected from their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer righteous principles. Now how can ſuch good <hi>Patriots of their Countrey</hi> but <hi>remember the days of old, and the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works of the Lord,</hi> how viſibly and powerfully his preſence was with them, when they conteſted againſt the <hi>Court party,</hi> and how he delivered them from the <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Bear, King</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and ſo have it (with much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance) upon their hearts, that he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135122:61"/>will help them ſtill, whilſt they open their mouth for the dumb, and plead the cauſe of the poor and needy. If a man ſee Beaſts in his field devouring the corn which himſelf had ſown, he cannot ſuffer it, but will drive them out. It may be ſaid in a good ſence, it was the <hi>old Parliament</hi> that ſowed this <hi>Commonwealth</hi> with much good ſeed, in order to the freedom, ſafety, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Nation. I hope therefore ſuch men will ſtand up again in the <hi>good old way,</hi> and ſeek to repair thoſe grievous breaches which have been made ſince, by a company of corrupt and deceitful men. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> Neh. 6.11.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Nehemiah</hi> upon his return to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaw what great evil had been done in his abſence, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things through the pride and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of ſome men were quite out of order, it not only grieved him, but ſtirr'd him up to endeavour a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Reformation. And no doubt, that which occaſioned him to ſhew himſelf ſo zealouſly earneſt in the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135122:61"/>work, it was, in that they had broken the good <hi>Government</hi> which he himſelf (as a principal man) had ſetled among them but a little before: ſee <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. If there be a <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in this <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (as I hope there are many) men that will ſeek the welfare of <hi>England;</hi> it is not an Apoſtate <hi>Eliaſhib,</hi> or a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant <hi>Tobiah,</hi> that they will fear; nor the <hi>Rulers,</hi> but will contend with them, and never ceaſe, till the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> be freed from oppreſſion and ſlavery, &amp; ſetled upon a righteous foundation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. I am the more encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to HOPE that this <hi>Parliament</hi> will be ſucceſsful in their undertakings, and highly bleſt by Almighty God: Becauſe there are ſome Army-<hi>Officers</hi> among them, who have kept their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and have not betrayed the <hi>good old Cauſe,</hi> for which they ingaged. I know it will be matter of much grief unto ſuch men, that they muſt now in a <hi>little</hi> room be ſtanding up for the publike intereſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which could not be obtain'd, till they had paſt thorow many places in
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135122:62"/>blood. Ah honeſt hearts! they little thought when they left their families, eſtates, Relations, and what elſe was dear unto them, and carried their lives in their hands, that they ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſit at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and hear the very ſame things pleaded for, which they had before deſtroyed. For what were the things for which they fought? Was it not againſt Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical and Arbitrary power? againſt proſecution of <hi>Court-Principles</hi> by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt men? Was it not to take off all oppreſſions from the necks of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England?</hi> Was it not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the long uſurped Authority of Lords Civil and Eccleſiaſtical over the Commons? was it not that the ſupreme Authority ſhould reſide originally in the people, according to the Law of God, light of Nature and right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? That all perſons ſhould own, and ſtand by that Commonwealth-conſtitution, as then eſtabliſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>King and Houſe of Lords?</hi> And that it ſhould be Treaſon for any man to be <hi>Chief Magiſtrate of England and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135122:62"/>without conſent of Parliament?</hi> was it not againſt all Negative <hi>voices</hi> over the free-people of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? and againſt the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> to be ſetled and kept in the hands of any ſingle Perſon? Let the enemies themſelves be Judges, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe were not the main things conteſted for againſt the late King, and for the recovery whereof, the <hi>Nations Truſtees in Parliament</hi> ingaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the good People thereof, in a long, expenſive, and bloody War, which (by the good hand of God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting them) ended in the total ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of their adverſaries, and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating them to execute exemplary Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon the principal and his abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Surely, theſe old <hi>Souldiers</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this to be true, have not ſo far left their former valour and reſolution, as now to give all up unto men far more inconſiderable then the Royal party was. If men ſhould ſee a company of Boys over their heads, throwing down ſtones upon them; I know what they would do in ſuch a caſe. I ſhall leave
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135122:63"/>the application to the Reader.</p>
               <p>But I hear the Noble Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> is choſen for a <hi>Parliament-man.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it was not <hi>a perſonal grudge to the Houſe of the Stuarts,</hi> nor any particular diſcontent he had againſt the ancient Nobility and Gentry of the Nation, that he cut them down in all places where he came; but rather his love to truth and righteouſneſs. Howbeit his ſilence of late is much wondered at, and his friends do now expect that he will appear (like himſelf) againſt the <hi>new Court party,</hi> and our <hi>yeſterday Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> (ſo far as in point of honour and conſcience he is bound) and make it evident, it was no perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſpight againſt the King and his party that he fought them, but love to his Country.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. May not we <hi>HOPE</hi> now, that iniquity ſhall ſtop her mouth? <hi>The fear of you, and the dread of you, ſhall be upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very beaſt of the Earth,</hi> Gen. 9.2. Though there may be in ſome a <hi>will and de ſire,</hi> that the ſeveral burdens &amp; grievances of the people ſhould not be taken
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135122:63"/>off, nor any thing done to ſettle and provide for the ſafety, ſettlement, and welfare of the Nation by common conſent; Nevertheleſs, men of <hi>publick Spirits,</hi> and <hi>righteous principles,</hi> now <hi>ſpeaking</hi> for the <hi>good old cauſe,</hi> and <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> againſt the exerciſe of Arbitrary power over the lives, Liberties, and Eſtates of the people; Now <hi>declaring</hi> againſt ſetting up a particular intereſt tending to the reviving of the <hi>Barons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wars,</hi> by a ſucceſſive contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two diſtinct perſons and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies for the Soveraignty; Now <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> againſt perſons of a degenerate, ſlaviſh, and enſlaving ſpirit, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging and joyning with the old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, and acting and appearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, directly oppoſite to thoſe good principles and things formerly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. When theſe, and ſuch like things ſhall be ſpoken, what may be expected then? <hi>A fear and dread, what will follow if there ſhould be any contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> and no marvel, <hi>the burnt child fears the fire.</hi> It is too well known, how deeply ſome have ſuffered already for
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135122:64"/>raſh ingaging themſelves for a <hi>Court-intereſt</hi> againſt the juſt rights of the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>When he put on righteouſneſs, and brake the jaws of the wicked, and pluckt the ſpoil out of their teeth; delivered the poor that cried, and cauſed the widdows heart to ſing for joy: The young men hid themſelves, and the aged ſtood up. The Princes refrained talking, and laid their hand on their mouth. The nobles held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth,</hi> Job 29. There hath not been of late time, ſuch a time as this is, for righteous <hi>Jobs</hi> (eſpecially in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>) to plead for Juſtice. For rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, no man can think (as the caſe of the Nation ſtands) that any perſon will have the forehead to ſpeak (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he think) againſt the freedom, ſafety, and welfare of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> which yet he muſt do, if he ſpeak for the preſent <hi>abuſes and Court-corruptions,</hi> for which the Parliament and Army engaged againſt the late King. <hi>Fear not, there ſhall not a man be able to ſtand before thee,</hi> Joſh. 5.1.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:135122:64"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 6. It is the <hi>hope</hi> of many (and herein I am not without <hi>hope</hi>) under that huge heap of chaff, (I mean the Army) there is ſome good corn; ſome fire among the abundance of aſhes: if ſo, it will now appear; that is, ſuch among them as ſtill love the <hi>Good old cauſe,</hi> ſpeak high for righteous things, and ſeem to mourn for the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie of the Army, they will cloſe with the <hi>preſent Parliament,</hi> to have Arbitrary power put down, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>Birth-rights</hi> reſtored, and ſtand no longer with a corrupt intereſt againſt equity, Law, and conſcience.</p>
               <p>Before the Lord deſtroyed <hi>Sodom,</hi> he brought <hi>Lot</hi> out of it: who knows but by this <hi>Parliament</hi> the Lord will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his choſen ones in the Army from his wrath he means to pour upon the reſt? it is no matter though they are few. <hi>There is no reſtraint to the Lord to ſave by many or by few,</hi> 1 Sam. 14.6. I know ſome can hardly beleeve, that the Lord will ſo far honour them, as to imploy them in his <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But let no mans eye be evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135122:65"/>God is good; he is wiſer then man, and knows better then he what is to be done. Conſidering therefore what an opportunity is now put into their hands by this <hi>Parliament,</hi> there is <hi>hope,</hi> that our Heavenly Father (who is kind to the unkind) is tendring mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to them as he did to <hi>Lot.</hi> Beſides, there are few in the Army of honeſt Principles, but do very well know, if the <hi>Parliament</hi> do not ſtand to effect good things for the Nation, there will be little ſafety for them in the Army. For the conteſt begins now between the <hi>two old Intereſts,</hi> the <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Round-heads</hi> or <hi>Cavaleers;</hi> no hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhortly between two opinions, but either back again where we were <hi>into the Houſe of Bondage,</hi> or forward in <hi>a free Commonwealth</hi> for more Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Again. It muſt needs be matter of grief to many Souldiers, to conſider what ſad diviſions and rents there are among the people of God about them; many tender conſciences not being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to have <hi>ſpiritual communion</hi> with
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135122:65"/>them, becauſe of their ſupporting an <hi>Arbitrary power.</hi> They may ſay, it is of their weakneſs in judgment: let it be ſo, yet they cannot be without deep ſence of theſe diviſions (as I hope they are,) and therefore they will look upon this thing as a great Providence, that they ſhall now come under the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Parliament,</hi> to ſerve their Country honeſtly, and not the licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of lawleſs perſons any more. And this will greatly tend to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and peace among Chriſtians. And whereas Parliaments of late have been overſwayed by <hi>Sword-men;</hi> yea, often broken to peeces at their pleaſure: it is <hi>hoped</hi> now, that theſe Army-men (of whom I ſpeak) will prevent all ſuch fear and danger, by giving up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>obedience of the Parliament,</hi> and openly declare, that they will ſtand with them to have the <hi>Good old Cauſe</hi> up again, and the undoubted Rights and Liberties of theſe Nations fixt upon the right foundation of truth and righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 7. When this <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135122:66"/>the ſtraits of the Nation, and how many ways the well-affected to our freedom and juſt rights have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; yea, been undone in their perſons and eſtates, contrary to Law and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and who have been the cauſe of all this (as we hope they will hear the grievances of the people) it is not to be doubted, but there will be an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> with a witneſs: <hi>Knoweſt thou not yet, that Egypt is deſtroyed?</hi> Exod. 10.7. as if they ſhould ſay, The land is waſted, the people impoveriſhed, and that little which is left us, will ſoon be taken from us, if thou ſend not away this people. Thus will be the cry of the Nation to the <hi>Parliament</hi> (if they ſit a little while) and they will hear it with both ears: Sirs, <hi>Know ye not that England is deſtroyed? our Merchants break dayly, all trade fails us, many fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies periſh; and that little which is left in the land the Court will devour, if it be not diſmiſt by your wiſdom and care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one thing (and very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) this <hi>Parliament</hi> will remember and make uſe of; it was the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135122:66"/>of ſome, in <hi>breaking one Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after another,</hi> that they did it for TRYAL. And ſo this laſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſet up, as judged the beſt and moſt expedient for publick good. The <hi>Long Parliament</hi> was too ſlow, and the <hi>little Parliament</hi> was too quick, and therefore a <hi>new Instrument</hi> muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd to ſave the Nation. Now I hope there is no wrong done to the <hi>Tryers,</hi> if this <hi>Parliament</hi> having found by proof and ſad experience, that of the three changes the laſt was the worſt, (I ſay) granting this, if they ſhould (follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the others example) lay it aſide, and take up ſomething elſe. Nay more, how can the Parliament (as the <hi>peoples Trustees</hi>) be faithful, if they ſhall find that the better Government was laid aſide, and the worſer ſet up, almoſt to the undoing of the Nation, and yet let it ſtand?</p>
               <p>It is a Maxime in State, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Civil, When corruptions and abuſes do ariſe, to reduce things to their firſt inſtitution. Thus Chriſt in refuting the <hi>Phariſees</hi> about plurality of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135122:67"/>wives, mentioneth the firſt <hi>inſtitution of marriage: From the beginning it was not ſo,</hi> Mat. 19.8. So <hi>Paul</hi> in ſeeking to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs the diſorders in the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> about the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ſets down the <hi>Institution,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. and this I <hi>hope</hi> will be the practiſe of the Parliament in ſeeking to reform the many grievances of the Nation, to bring things to the Original; that is, when the Government was changed from <hi>Monarchy</hi> to a <hi>Commonwealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 8. I never had of late yeers more <hi>hope</hi> then now, of a good accord among all the <hi>Godly of the Houſe,</hi> under what form or name ſoever, that they will as one man ſtand up for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things. Indeed matters of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>former Parliaments</hi> have greatly obſtructed the ſettlement of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A rock under water is perillous: medling with Religion is the more dangerous, becauſe it is covered over with ſpecious and fair pretences, as if God would not bleſs Parliaments, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they begin <hi>at the Houſe of God;</hi> and here preſently they are at a loſs about
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:135122:67"/>
                  <hi>this Houſe of God,</hi> what it is, and where it is, there being ſo many, <hi>Lo here, and lo there.</hi> But I ſhall wave this diſcourſe. Whatſoever duty lies upon <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> concerning Religion, I am ſure as the affairs of the Nation now ſtand, there is ſome other thing to be lookt after: and if thoſe who are religious, mind it not, it is poſſible the <hi>Cavaleer</hi> (watching his opportunity) will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive both <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c. of all their <hi>Birth-right</hi> and freedom here in <hi>England;</hi> and where will they go next for liberty of Conſcience?</p>
               <p>There are (as I ſaid before) but <hi>two great Intereſts</hi> in the Nation, the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi> and <hi>Cavaleer;</hi> if the <hi>Cavaleer</hi> get it not, there is no fear, but all truly fearing God, will enjoy much love and peace together.</p>
               <p>Our Chronicles tell us, Never had the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> conquered us, had it not been for our own <hi>diviſions.</hi> If we loſe our <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and with it our Liberties and Lives, and the <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers</hi> have it, and from them <hi>Charls Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:135122:68"/>(for they play the old game under a new dreſs) I ſay, ſhould ſuch a thing be (which God forbid) it muſt be by the ſubtilty of the Enemy cauſing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion among good men, whereby their hands are made weak: but I hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, and ſpeak it for this end, <hi>As men are godly, ſo they ſhould be wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have ſhewed the grounds of my HOPE: what the actings and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of God will be for this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, a little time will ſhew. I know few of them; yet this I know, never did the condition of <hi>England</hi> require men of large parts, of wiſdom, integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of publick and unintereſted ſpirits more then now. I wiſh therefore there be no <hi>Boys</hi> for <hi>Men;</hi> no time-ſervers, flatterers, light, careleſs, and vain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, inſtead of honeſt, faithful, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, ſober, ſolid, and wiſe hearted. Their work is great, in a manner to ſave poor <hi>England,</hi> and to bring her off thoſe rocks whereon ſhe is ready to ſplit, into a ſafe Harbor. With reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence therefore to the phraſe, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things!</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:135122:68"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:135122:69"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:135122:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:135122:70"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:135122:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
